music
music
applause
applause
thank you
thank you
This is September's Feast of Knowledge
這是9月份的知識饗宴
This topic is very attractive
這次的題目是非常吸引人的
One topic is related to the history of medicine
一個題目是跟醫學歷史有關的
I actually wanted to hear this
本來事實上就想要來聽這個
speech
演講
It just so happened that our other vice president was in charge of this
正好我們另外副院長本來是主持這個的
Vice President Huang
黃副院長
He's abroad so he asked me to host
他在國外所以他找我來主持
I am honored to be the host of this feast of knowledge
我很榮幸來做這次知識饗宴的主持人
this time
這次的
The speaker is Dr. Lei Xianglin
主講人是雷祥林博士
he has very
他有非常
unique background
獨特的背景
It is
現在是
Associate Researcher of the Prohibition Institute in the Institute of Prohibition Institutes is also
禁止研究所中研究院禁止研究所的副研究員也是
Associate Professor at the Institute of Technology and Society, Yangming University
陽明大學科技與社會研究所的副教授
He graduated from the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University, and is also my alma mater and alma mater.
他是畢業於國立台灣大學化學系也是我的母校跟母系
so he is
所以他是
this is mine
這是我的
Junior is equal to a generation
學弟等於是一個generation
Then at the University of Chicago he switched to history
然后接着在芝加高大学他又转到学历史
He also has a master's degree in chemistry from the University of Chicago
他也拿到芝加高大学化学的硕士学位
The University of Chicago is also my alma mater
芝加高大学也是我的母校
Or my doctorate over there is also my junior
或者那边的我的博士学位也是我的学弟
So it's rare to have this background of chemistry and history
所以有这种化学又是历史的背景是很难得的
But it's also about chemistry
但是也是说是学化学
I'm a helper to learn chemistry Chemistry publicity
我是一帮面帮学化学化学宣传一下
Many of us in the courtyard are chemistry students
我们在院里不少是化学的
Like the seniors or juniors in my past department
像我的过去系里面前后的学长或学弟
I don't know in the life science group
在生命科学组就不晓得
There are quite a few who used to be directors
就有好几位过去当所长
There are vice presidents
有当副院长的
But I'm honored for the first time
但是我第一次很荣幸的
Now one is from chemistry to history
现在一位是从化学转到历史的
published numerous articles
發表無數的文章
But one article worth mentioning is
但是有一篇值得提的就是
Nilidonky No Horse Medicine in the struggle over China's modernity
Nilidonky No Horse Medicine in the struggle over China's modernity
published by the university
是自家大學出版的
Published in 2014
在2014年出版
This one once won the American Medical History Society class
這一個曾經獲得美國醫學史學會班的
William Welch Medal in 2016
William Welch Medal在2016年
Then I also won this award in the Humanities and Social Sciences Special Book Award of Academia Sinica
然後在中研院人文與社會科學專書獎也拿到這個獎
It was responsible for promoting the openness of Taiwan's science and technology and social academic network
它曾經負責推動開放性的台灣科技與社會學術網路
this is a three year plan
這是一個三年計畫
From 2001 to 2004
從2001年到2004
The next long-term participation was initiated by Taiwanese scholars
接下來長期參與由台灣學者發起
The international academic journal edited by him is called East Asian Science Technology and Society
與主編的國際學術期刊叫做East Asian Science Technology and Society
This is an International Journal
這是一個International Journal
is published by Duke University
是Duke University出版的
In 2016, this year began to take over the
2016年就今年開始接任該
Please warmly welcome the protagonist Dr. Lei
請各位熱烈歡迎雷博士主角
Thank you, Dean Dr. Lei, for your introduction
謝謝雷博士院長的介紹
I would like to thank the hospital for giving me this opportunity to make this report with you
我要謝謝院方給我這個機會跟大家做這個報告
Of course, I would also like to thank everyone advanced
當然還要更感謝各位先進
and colleagues and friends
還有同仁和朋友們
After a day of hard work is over
在一天這麼辛勞的工作完了
Only dare to listen to this speech after get off work
只有下班還敢來聽這個演講
When you see the topic of today's speech
大家看到今天這個演講題目的時候
It should be a bit of a surprise
應該會覺得有一點意外
Because these two topics and subtopics
因為這兩個主題跟副題
Looks like it's only set to quite different things
看起來只設到相當不同的事情
The main title is the name of Du Congming's Chinese meaning to study
主標題杜聰明的漢義要研究之名
Seems like a very specific case
好像是一個很具體的個案
That is to say, of course it is Mr. Du Congming, who everyone knows
就是說當然是大家都知道的杜聰明先生
but only a very small part of his research
但只關於他的研究中的一個很小的部分
sounds like a very case study
聽起來是一個非常個案的研究
But the subtitle Traditional Medicine and Modernity in East Asia
可是副標題傳統醫療與東亞的現代性
sounds like a big topic
聽起來就像一個很大的題目
and it seems to have a lot of meaning and probing
而且似乎有很大的意涵和追問式的
This is indeed a design for my speech today
這的確是今天我做這個演講的一個設計
I want to talk about a specific individual
我想從一個具體的個人來談一個
Maybe many people will care
可能很多人都會關心
and has not been adequately answered
而且還沒有被充分回答
an issue that is debated even today
甚至到今天都在爭議之中的問題
So maybe it is not the same as the goal of our knowledge experiment today.
所以也許跟我們今天這個知識的想驗的目標不太一樣
What I share with you today is not so much knowledge
就今天我跟大家分享的與其說是知識
Of course there is knowledge
當然是有知識啦
But to a greater extent, it may be to share with you
可是更大的程度上可能是要跟大家分享
Questions that are still debated today
一些到今天還在爭議之中的疑問
then please let me try first
那就請讓我先來設法
Let’s start from solving the big problem of the subtitle
從解副標題這個大問題開始來說明
The question I want to share with you today
我今天想跟大家分享的問題
What Vice President Liu said just now meant that
剛剛那個劉副院長說到就是說
I graduated from the Department of Chemistry
我是化學系畢業的
indeed so
的確如此
from a certain point of view
在某個角度上來講
This is the issue that we are concerned about in this speech or my research
這個我們這個演講或者說我研究所關心的問題
It's actually a very simple question.
其實是一個非常素樸的問題
It's a question that a chemistry student would also think of
是一個化學系的大學生也會想到的問題
That is to say, all kinds of traditional East Asian knowledge about nature
就是說傳統東亞關於自然的各種知識
From 1900 to present
從1900年到現在
The world has been completely replaced by modern science
世界以來都已經被現代科學所全盤取代了
Why Only Traditional Medicine Is the Only Accident
為什麼只有傳統醫學是唯一的意外
exception
例外
Why Chinese medicine is still active in our life today
為什麼中醫到今天仍然活躍在我們的生活中
and even spread back to the rest of the world
甚至反向傳到世界各地
Come to think of it, this is indeed a rather strange phenomenon.
大家想想看這的確是一個蠻奇怪的現象
right
對不對
That is to say, a student who has never studied history
就是說而且是一個沒有學過歷史的話學系的學生
also start to feel curious
也會開始覺得好奇的問題
from a certain angle
某個角度上來講
I'm a historian trying to answer
我做一個歷史學家想要回答
that is
就是說
what kind of historical process
是什麼樣的一個歷史過程
This led to such a peculiar phenomenon
才導致了這樣一個奇特的現象
We want to know the course of history
我們想知道歷史的過程
more importantly i think
更重要的是我想
Many people here will care
在座很多人都會關心的
What is the significance of this historical phenomenon
就這個歷史現象意義究竟何在
Does it mean that East Asia is still far behind?
是表示東亞還仍然很落後呢
Or does it mean there are other possibilities?
還是表示有其他的可能性呢
This should be a further question
這應該是更進一步的問題
that's my original
那這是我原始
A naive question that I think everyone will agree on
我想大家都會同意的一個素樸的問題
But many simple questions that everyone cares about
可是很多大家都關心的素樸的問題
Historians are unlikely to be able to solve
歷史學家都不見得能夠解決
So I'm going to
所以我下面要
Use two specific historical scenes to present a
用兩個具體的歷史場景來跟大家呈現一個
A specific question that we are better able to answer than historians
我們比歷史學家比較能回答的一個具體的問題
The first of these two historical scenarios takes place in 1925
這兩個歷史場景第一個發生在1925年
This is Dr. Sun Yat-sen trying at Union Hospital in Beijing.
這個是孫中山試試在北京的協和醫院
Before he tried it, he already knew that liver cancer was incurable.
他在試試以前已經知道得肝癌已經沒有救了
Then what about that time
然後那個時候呢
Whether he should take traditional Chinese medicine before dying
他究竟臨死前要不要吃中藥的事情
become a matter of national concern
就成為全國都非常關心的問題
Everyone wants to know the one who overthrew the Qing Dynasty
大家都想知道一個推翻滿清的一個
leader of the revolution
革命的領導人
Did he take Chinese medicine when he was weakest?
會不會在他最軟弱的時候吃了中藥
He himself has medical training
他自己還有醫學的訓練呢
right
對不對
That means he was at his weakest at the end of his life
那就意味著他在最後臨終最軟弱的時候
Abandoned what he believed in science and modernity
被棄他所相信的科學和現代性
while taking traditional Chinese medicine
而服用中藥
So the newspapers report every day
所以報紙每天都在報
Let's see if he will give in
看他究竟會不會屈服下來
that was the situation
那是當時的情形
what about later
那後來呢
among those who care
關心這件事情的人之中
Another Lu Xun who also studied medicine in Japan
另外一位也是曾經在日本學醫的魯迅
After Sun Yat-sen passed away, he once wrote that
他在孫中山過世之後他曾經寫說
He once heard that Sun Yat-sen refused to take traditional Chinese medicine
他一度聽說孫中山拒服中藥
In fact, Sun Yat-sen took Chinese medicine in the end
其實孫中山最後還是服了中藥
In addition, he was consigned to the Xiehe Hospital for taking traditional Chinese medicine.
而且為了服中藥還被協和醫院
Ask him to move out of the hospital before he can take Chinese medicine
要求他搬出醫院才能服食中藥
But once Lu Xun heard that Sun Yat-sen refused to take traditional Chinese medicine
但一度魯迅聽說孫中山不服中藥
He said the news that Sun Yat-sen refused to take traditional Chinese medicine
他說孫中山拒服中藥的消息
No less than his lifetime revolutionary cause touched me
不下於他一生革命事業的感動過我
Even the overthrow of the Qing Dynasty has not moved him so much
就是推翻滿清還沒有讓他那麼感動
He still doesn't take Chinese medicine at this time
他在這個時候還不服中藥
That makes him feel really touched
才讓他覺得真正很感動
So you can imagine that
所以大家可以想像就是說
at this point in time
在這個時間點
Whether to take traditional Chinese medicine or not is not a small problem of personal health
服中藥與否不是一個個人健康的小問題
Rather, it represents a major issue in the development of a country
而是代表一個國家發展的大問題
so everyone will be very concerned
所以每個人都會非常關心
And Lu Xun gave him such a high importance
而且魯迅給了他一個這麼高的重要性
This is in 1925 and 1926
這是在1925跟1926
but after half a century
但是在半個世紀之後
This meaning is almost reversed
這個意義卻幾乎遭到反轉
still in the same hospital
仍然是在同樣一個醫院
Still at Peking Union Medical College Hospital
還是在北京協和醫院
It's one that's heavily supported by the Rockefeller Foundation.
就是洛克菲勒基金會大力支持的一個
The most advanced hospital in East Asia at that time
東亞當時最先進的醫院裡
that is very famous
就是說非常有名
Just to visit with Nixon
就是伴隨著尼克森去訪問
Interviewed by a New York Times reporter
訪問的一個紐約時報的記者
James Reston
James Reston
He had an operation and was admitted to this hospital
他在當時開刀而住進這個醫院
At that time the hospital had been renamed
那時候這個醫院已經改名叫
Anti-land hospital
反地醫院了
Then after he went in
然後他進去之後呢
Received some weeks of treatment during surgery
開刀的時候接受了一些徵周的治療
He found it very miraculous
結果他覺得非常的神奇
He later interviewed some of the patients inside
後來他還訪問了一些在裡面的病人
And feel the amazing effect
而感覺到有驚人的療效
So he was later in the New York Times
所以他後來在紐約時報上
published an article
發表了一篇專文
Where is the special article?
那邊專文呢
It also starts from today's special article
也是從今天專文開始
Only Americans have heard the term AcuPuncture
美國人才聽到AcuPuncture這個徵周這個詞
Syndromal fever
而引發了徵周熱
Well James Reston knows very well
那James Reston非常清楚的知道
how ironic this thing is
這件事有多大的反諷
When the hospital was established
當年成立這個醫院的時候
the Logefeller Foundation
就是洛格菲勒基金會
In order to introduce the spirit of science into China
為了要把科學的精神引入中國
and built up
而建立起來的
Unexpectedly, after receiving treatment here, he
沒想到他卻在這裡面接受了治療之後
And believe that China has created a
而相信中國創造出了一個
Symptoms unknown to other modern medicine
其他現代醫療都不知道的徵周
And combine the old medical treatment with the new
而且把舊的醫療跟新的
medical together
医疗结合在一起
It seems that China has developed another
仿佛中国发展出了另外一种
Effective medical treatment that the world does not know
世人所不知的有效的医疗
To expand a little
扩大一点来讲
It's like another kind of modernity
好像是另外一种现代性
so it feels a strong irony
所以它感到一个强烈的反讽
And this also triggered the whole
而且这个也是后来引发了整个
The real origins of the alternative medical craze
另类医疗的热潮的真就热的起源
Then the two scenes I'm showing you now
那我现在给大家看到的这两个场景
50 years apart in the same hospital
在同一个医院里相隔50年
Almost the entire Chinese medicine or traditional medicine
几乎整个中医或传统医疗
Relationship to Science and Relationship to Modernity
跟科学的关系和现代性的关系
reversed
遭到反转
If in order to let everyone feel more deeply
那如果为了让大家更深切的感觉到
How big is this reversal
这个反转的规模有多大
Let's look at another gentleman's lecture
我们再来看另外一个先生的讲法
This is Fu Sinian, who once served as the president of National Taiwan University after the war
这是曾经在战后担任台大校长的傅思年
He said that I would not consult Chinese medicine even when I was dying.
他说我是临死也不请教中医的
I feel that if I don't, I'm sorry for my education.
我觉得若不如此就对不住我所受的教育
So he has a very strong stance
所以他是有一个非常激烈的立场
And what's more
而且更进一步的呢
In 1934 he published an essay
他在1934年发表一篇专文
He said
他说
The most shameful, hateful and breathless thing in China now is
中國現在最可恥最可恨最令人氣短的是
It's not a bandit exchange, it's not a foreign exchange
不是匪換不是外換
It should be the so-called dispute between Chinese and Western medicine
而應是所謂的中西醫之爭
This is almost the same as what Lu Xun said
這幾乎跟魯迅的講法是一樣
At that time, the Northeast was completely occupied by the prison army.
那時候東北已經完全被獄軍佔領了
But he thinks it's more shameful than such a foreign exchange
但他覺得比起這樣的外換比起來更可恥的
There is still the so-called dispute between Chinese and Western medicine
還是有所謂中西醫之間的這個爭執
he said why
他說為什麼呢
Because they think they are advocating waiting
因為自己認為自己在提倡靜待化的人
common sense of science
對於很容易分辨的科學常識
still in chaos
還在混沌的狀態中
let alone more complicated things
何況比較複雜的事情
To this day, I still come there to compete for Chinese and Western medicine
到今天還來那裡爭著中西醫
Wouldn't it make people all over the world think that the Chinese are a kind of human beings from another world?
豈不是使全世界的人都覺得中國人是另世人類的一種
The school that has been in operation for 40 years still cannot break away from this medieval stage
辦了40年的學校還不能脫離這個中世紀的階段
Doesn't it make people feel that the future of education is still the same
豈不叫人覺得教育的前途仍是往然
he said very serious things
就他說非常重的話
Especially here is a special mention of waiting
特別在這邊特別標舉出了一個靜待化
is what I call the concept of modernity
就是我稱之為現代性的概念
then i want here
那我在這裡想要
Here you can in this seemingly simple sentence
在這裡大家可以在這段看起來簡單的話裡
Actually there are many
其實有非常多
I explained why the discussion on China and the West was so important at that time
我说明了为什么当时对中西的论真是这么重要
An important matter that is not allowed to be decided by individuals
不容许个人来决定的一个重大的事情
because it actually touches on a debate about modernity
就是因为它事实上涉及了一个关于现代性的辩论
How should I put it, we just looked at, for example, the first element
怎么说呢 我们刚刚看 比如第一个元素
The meaning of modernity basically means that
现代性的意义基本上来讲就是说
We determine Europe's experience in modern development
我们规决欧洲在近代发展的经验
And there seems to be a general trend
而好像得到了一个普遍的趋势
feel that all people in the world
觉得全部 全世界的人
Feel like the whole world is going the same way
觉得整个世界都走向同样的
Everybody's heading for the nation-state, capitalism, the industrial revolution
大家都走向民族国家 资本主义 工业革命
even the acceptance of science and so on
甚至于那个接受科学等等
Therefore, in this universal direction of common development
所以在这个普世的一个共同发展的方向上
If you still have to develop another contingency alone
如果你仍然单独要发展另外一个意料的话
It's as if you've become different from everyone else
好像你变成跟其他人全部都不一样
Not in line with the trend of universal development
而不符合普世发展的趋势
Second, if you are really different from others
第二呢 就是如果你真的跟人家不一样的话
Your difference is not what we call multiculturalism today
你的不同不是像我们今天所说的多元文化
Different cultures have different values
不同的文化有不同的价值
People will tell you that what you're talking about is familiar to me
別人會告訴你說 你講的是我很熟悉
Just a few hundred years ago we were in the medieval stage
就在幾百年前 我們在中世紀階段
We advocate the same medicine during the dark period
在黑暗階段的時候 我們也是提倡同樣的醫學
So this difference is not considered a value
所以這個不同呢 不會被當成一個價值
Instead it would clearly be seen as a previous period in history
反而會很清楚的被視為一個歷史的前一階段
And going a step further
而且再更進一步來講
This why is that in such a European experience
這個為什麼就是說 在這樣的一個歐洲的經驗中
they will get the perception
他們會得到這樣的看法
Some even Europeans feel
有一部分就是 歐洲人也覺得
Developments from the 17th century are not just new phases of history
從17世紀來的發展 不只是歷史的新的階段而已
is an unprecedented stage
是一個史無前例的階段
We know the truth about the world like never before
我們史無前例的知道了世界的真相
That is to say, it is completely different from the past
就是說 而跟以往完全不同
In this sense, the most representative
在這個意義上來講 最有代表的
It's modern science
其實就是現代科學
Wait until our Newtonian almanac, wait until the Newtonian almanac is invented
等到我們牛頓歷學 等到牛頓歷學發明了之後
We don't feel like we're just entering a new phase
我們不覺得我們只是進入一個新的階段而已
It's the feeling that everyone in the past was wrong
而是感覺到以往的人全部都錯了
We know the truth about nature like never before
我們史無前例的知道了關於自然的真理
and thus bring us to the front
也因此使我們跟前面
premodern people were completely different
前現代的人完全不同
So from this point of view
所以在這個角度來講
In fact, science has been around throughout our modern history
其實科學在我們整個現代史
My research unit is modern history
我在的研究單位是現代史
it has a very special meaning
它是有一個非常特別的意義
That is to say, if we talk about the political system
就是說如果說關於政治制度
female role
女性的角色
In other words, the relationship between the state, politics and religion
或者說國家跟政治跟宗教的關係
If there is room for debate among cultures
各文化間還有辯論的餘地的話
It shouldn't be hard for everyone to question
應該大家都不會很難質疑說
Science has the highest generality
科學有最高的普通性
And we clearly see the progress of science
而且我們清楚看到科學的進步
and we clearly see
而且我們清楚的看到
There is a very big break between science and the past
科學跟以前間有非常大的斷裂
In the past, not only China had traditional Chinese medicine
以往不只中國有中醫
The West also has their traditional Greek medicine
西方也有他們傳統的希臘醫療
But those can be completely given up
可是那些都可以完全的放棄
without any hesitation
而不必有任何的遲疑
we know those are wrong
我們知道那些都錯了
Those have only historical value
那些都只有歷史的價值而已
So from this point of view
所以在這個角度來講
science as modernity
所謂作為現代性的科學
That is to say that science makes us feel most clearly
就是說科學讓我們最清楚的感覺到
developed in Europe
這個歐洲所發展出來的
Many of these systems have developed
發展出來的很多這一系列的制度
is of universal value
是有普世價值
And it deserves a system that the people embrace from a new perspective
而且值得人民從全新擁抱的制度
So from this point of view
所以在這個角度來講
Original European Modern History Experience
原來歐洲的現代史的經驗
It is no longer just a historical experience
就不再只是一個歷史經驗而已
and became a normative concept
而成為了一個規範性的概念
or in this era
或者說在這個時代的時候
Some would say the concept of civilization
有人會說的文明這個概念
people of other nationalities
其他國家的民族的人
There is no need to examine their
不需要再仔細的檢討他們的
Every part of historical and cultural knowledge
歷史文化知識的每一個部分
you know you should start with
你就知道你應該以
Europe's historical experience and development direction
歐洲這個歷史經驗和發展方向
as a development direction
作為發展方向
because that's the way to go
因為那就是正確的方向
So from this point of view
所以在這個角度來講
you can see
大家可以看出來
in this sense
就是在這個意義上
Just now Fu Sinian would feel
剛剛傅思年會覺得
The Importance of Discussion about China and the West
關於中西的論真重要所在
Because suppose once you admit
因為假設你一旦承認了
you are in east asia
你在東亞
your whole european experience
你在整個歐洲經驗中
they all give up their own
他們都放棄他們自己的
Pre-Modern Medical Cases
前現代的醫學情況下
and you read the same
而你讀書一致
keep another
另外保留一個
self-proclaimed scientific medicine
自稱有科學性的醫學的話
make you different from the whole world
就使得你跟全世界都不一樣
It seems to mean that there are many different possibilities for the development of this world
仿佛意味著這個世界的發展還有很多種不同的可能
right
對不對
That's what Fu Sinian said
那這也是傅思年說的
If you can't even distinguish such a clear thing
如果連這麼清楚的事情都分不清楚的話
As for the development of other political aspects of society
那關於社會的其他的政治各方面的發展
There will be countless debates that can take place
更會有無數的辯論可以發生了
so for them
所以對他們來講
It's a matter of life and death
這件事情是有關生死的大事
That's why there was so much debate
就是為什麼當時會有這麼多人的辯論
But at that time, in order to ask questions about Chinese medicine
而當時其實為了要關於中醫的問題
triggering the resignation of the chief executive at the time
引發當時的行政人員長要辭職
So it should be regarded as the truth of nuclear four in the 1920s and 2030s.
所以應該算是1920、2030年代的核四的論真吧
At that time, this was a very political theory
當時這是非常高的政治性的一個論真
So from this point of view
所以在這個角度上來講
I started from Su Pu's question just now
我從剛剛素普的問題出發
When I turn this question into a specific historical question
我把這個問題變成一個具體的歷史問題的時候
we can say
我們可以來這樣說
It is how Chinese medicine has developed within half a century
就是中醫如何在半個世紀之內
sworn enemy of modernity
由現代性的死敵
what we think must be excluded
我們認為一定要排斥的東西
and transformed into Chinese exploration and modernity
而轉化成中國探索及現代性
The most concrete symbols and tools
最具體的象徵和工具
That's what I was going to ask
那這個就是我本來我所要追問
And one of my specific historical questions
而且我的一個具體的歷史問題
It's also what Vice President Liu just mentioned
也是劉副院長剛剛提到就是說
I'm writing a book about it
我為此寫一本專書
The Chinese name is "Fei Aluminum Fei Ma"
中文的名字叫《非鋁非馬
Medicine and China's Modernity Controversy"
醫學和中國的現代性之爭》
But what?
可是呢
I don't want to come with you today
我今天不想跟大家來
talk about the content of this book
講這本書的內容
On the one hand, there is no way to do it in one speech.
一方面也是沒辦法在一個演講中完成
on the other hand
另外一方面
So I want to change a perspective to share with you
所以我想換一個角度來跟大家分享
possible problems in this history
這個歷史中可能的問題
And I hope you feel that in this history
而希望大家覺得這段歷史中
Contains more complex issues than we originally thought
包含的問題比我們原來想像的還複雜
still interesting
還有趣
but also
而且還
still under debate
目前還在辯論中
And it's worth taking a serious look at him
而且值得我們認真的來看他
That
那
This brings me to the main title of my speech today
這就涉及到我今天演講的主標題
it is me
就是我
i started from a
我從一個
related but otherwise distinct context
相關但另外不同的脈絡
It is the context of Mr. Du Congming
就是杜聰明先生的脈絡
To answer the historical development just now
來回答剛剛的這段歷史發展
The problem
的問題
Mr. Du Congming, everyone should be the most familiar scientist
杜聰明先生大家都應該是最熟悉不過的科學家
He Taiwan's first doctor of medicine
他台灣的第一位醫學博士
The first and third term of National Taiwan University School of Medicine
台大醫學院的第一任和第三任
The third dean
第三屆院長
And founded Kaohsiung Medical College
而且創辦高雄醫學院
on my story
在我這個故事上來講
he has a very important
他有一個非常重要的
an effort
一個努力
It was him from 1928 to 1929
就是他在1928年到1929年
Published an investigation on the research methods of Chinese Medicine
發表了一篇關於有關漢醫學研究方法的考察
At that time he had just returned to Taiwan
就那時候他剛回到台灣
The legend says that he built a Han medicine hospital
傳說說他建立一個漢醫醫院
and cause a
而引起一位
Than Mr. Qiyuan criticized him
比名叫啟源的先生批評他
As a result, Mr. Du was published in Taiwan Ming Pao
結果杜先生呢就在台灣明報上
Published 31 texts
發表了31篇文字
like this
像這樣子
Then a total of 31 articles were published in half a year
然後一共發表了半年31篇
Then there are a total of 60,000 words
然後一共有6萬字
So it's hard for everyone to imagine now
所以大家現在很難想像
is you in a
就是你在一個
Detailed scientific debate published in major large newspapers
主要的大型報紙上發表細部的科學辯論
It talks about a lot of history of science, chemical terms, etc.
裡面講一大堆的科學史化學名詞等等
But it took half a year
但就整整登了半年
Just one of mine is very important today
就今天我的一個很重要
The topics I will share with you later
我待會要跟大家分享的題材
It's from this article
就是從這篇文章裡出來的
that's not only it
那不僅是這樣子呢
And Mr. Du Congming
而且杜聰明先生
What about during the Japanese occupation and after the war?
在日治和戰後呢
Twice established Chinese medicine hospital
曾經兩度建立成立漢醫醫院
The first time was from 1928 to 1929 as I just said
第一次是我剛剛說的1928到1929
The second time was 1946, soon after the war
第二次就是戰後很快的1946
And it was not approved twice
而且兩次呢都不被同意
and the second time
而第二次的時候
It was after changing the principal after 228
就是在228之後換了校長之後
It should be Mr. Fu Sinian who put this
應該就是傅思年先生把這個他一度
To set up the program of Chinese Medicine Therapy Department
要成立漢醫治療科這個方案
canceled
給打消了
Then what about Du Congming
然後杜聰明呢
He also wanted to promote research in this area after the war
在戰後他也一直想要推動這方面的研究
Not only during the Japanese occupation period
不只在日治時期而已
He said I was in Taipei City University and National Taiwan University School of Medicine
他說我在台北地大和台大醫學院
For 20 years, I have taught students the history of traditional Chinese medicine
20年來都對學生講受中醫藥學史
Pharmacology of Traditional Chinese Medicine and Shanghan Theory
中藥藥物學和商涵論
make students get an idea
使學生得到一個觀念
I hope they can read Chinese medicine books
希望他們能讀中醫藥書籍
But recently, the Academic Affairs Office of National Taiwan University School of Medicine told me
可是最近呢台大醫學院的教務處跟我說
I don't have time, I can't schedule this class
沒有時間 排不下這個課了
So I terminate this handout
所以我終止這個講義
I created Kaohsiung Hospital by myself
我自己創高雄醫院
I'm going to teach in it myself
我自己要在裡面教
Later he created Gao Yi
後來他創了高義
he did teach
他的確去教了
Also published several books
而且還出了好幾本的專書
So we can see that
所以我們就可以看到就是說
his insistence on the matter
他對這件事的堅持
It's actually a lot of effort
就和投入的心力其實非常大
And many friends also know
而且非常多朋友也都知道
He has three famous studies
他有三個有名的研究
Regarding opium snake venom and traditional Chinese medicine
就鴉片蛇毒和漢藥
right
對不對
Then this is the famous third item
那這個就是其中很有名的第三項
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
I mentioned this to you
我跟大家提的這個
The secret of Chinese medicine research means
漢醫藥研究機密就是說
Du Congming, the leader of medical modernity in Taiwan
身為台灣醫學現代性領航人的杜聰明
Why do you support the pre-modern for a long time
為什麼會長期支持前現代的
Traditional East Asian Medicine
傳統東亞醫療
Now Mr. Du Congming's book
就現在杜聰明先生的書
We have a lot of books in Cobo
我們在科博書已經非常多了
But it seems that few of us come to discuss
可是似乎我們都很少有人來討論
this problem
這個問題
and more importantly
而且更重要的是說
not only he supports
不僅他支持
And his career is on his shoulders
而且他肩身中身的志業
persistently viewed as outdated
竟持續地被視為落伍的
acts against science
反對科學的行為
And because of this midterm he never had the means to build
而且因此中期生他從來沒有辦法建立
The Han medicine he wants to establish
他所要建立的漢醫
So this is what I call today
所以這是我今天稱之為的
Du Congming is well-known for his research on traditional Chinese medicine
杜聰明的漢醫藥研究知名
Then I try to share with you
那我試著想跟大家分享
I mean why on earth would he want to do this?
就是說他究竟為什麼會想要這麼做的原因
That is the main axis of my report to you below.
那這是我下面跟大家報告的主軸
I'll take off my coat then. I'm sorry.
那我脫一下外套好 對不起
I hope you all find this to be a puzzle.
希望大家會覺得這的確是個謎題喔
In this case, everyone will look forward to hearing some answers.
這樣的話大家會比較期待聽到一點答案
well that
好 那
The simplest way is to say
最簡單來講就是說
Let's start from just now and let me explain his example a little bit
我們從剛剛我先稍微再說明一下他這個例子
From the concept of modernity we just talked about
就從我們剛剛講的一個現代性的概念中來講
Well, in terms of the current concept
好 現在的概念中來講
This is the example we just mentioned
就是我們剛剛說的這個例子
In terms of the concept of modernity we just talked about
就是我們剛剛講的一個現代性的概念中來講
In fact, you are interested in pre-modern things
其實你對前現代的事情
Pre-Modern should be able to raise without hesitation
前現代應該可以毫無遲疑的揚起
right
對不對
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講呢
It should be clear that people can be divided into
人應該很清楚的可以分為
Modern Science and Traditional Conservation
現代科學跟傳統保守
So we just looked at, say, from
所以我們剛剛看 比如說從
Cong Sun Yat-sen Lu Xun Fu Sinian
從孫中山 魯迅 傅思年
They all think they are on the side of the modern
他們都自己認為站在現代的一邊
But if we compare modernity and science
可是要是要比起現代和科學的話
They should be far behind Du Congming
他們比起杜聰明應該都差得遠
right
對不對
In terms of his academic qualifications
就是以他的學術的資歷來講
They should be much worse than Du Congming
他們比起杜聰明應該都差得多
puzzling is to say
令人費解的就是說
Du Congming seems to have adopted a
杜聰明卻仿佛採取了一個
Viewed as a pro-traditional medical stance, at least at the time
至少在當時被視為支持傳統醫療的立場
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
Let's not talk about the answer to this mystery now
我們現在我們先不講這個謎的謎底
The case of Du Congming is very worthy of our careful consideration
杜聰明這個案例非常值得我們仔細來看
Because it's actually pretty easy for us to find other supportive people
因為我們其實很容易找到其他支持的人
But if other supporters previously
但如果以前其他支持人
we can easily say
我們很容易說
they have no scientific mind
他們沒有科學頭腦
they have a vested interest
他們有既得利益
or they themselves have no science
或他們自己沒有科學
do not understand
不了解
Science right?
科學對不對
But Du Congming, you can't say that about him
可是杜聰明你沒辦法這樣來說他
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
His case exemplifies a very large
他的個案就體現了一個非常大的一個
combine two irreconcilable elements
結合兩個不容調和的元素
thus presenting a great deal of inner tension and creativity
從而呈現出很大的內在緊張和創造性
So before I solve the problem
所以我在解題之前
I hope you can feel
我先希望大家可以感覺到
an inherently interesting aspect of the matter
這個事情的一個內在有趣的地方
But if we think about it further
但是我們進一步來想的話
How to understand Du Congming
就要怎麼了解杜聰明
when i was doing research in the city
當我在城市做研究的時候
I think of what a friend told me
我想到有一位朋友跟我說的話
At that time, Taipei 101 was the tallest building in the world.
那時候台北101大樓還是全世界最高的大樓
Then this friend is a foreign friend
然後這個朋友是一個外國朋友
he told me
他跟我說
But it doesn't seem to feel
可是看起來不太會感覺到
He is the tallest building in the world
他是世界最高的高樓
Later he told me that the reason was because
後來他自己跟我說原因就是因為
There are no other tall buildings nearby
旁邊沒有其他很高的高樓
so if you go to new york
所以如果你去紐約的話
You see the so-called sports building first
你先看到那個所謂運動大樓
That's 1901 high
那是1901高的
you can compare one by one
你就可以有一個個的比較
Do you know how tall that building is?
知道那個樓有多高對不對
If there are no other tall buildings next to Taipei 101
那如果台北101旁邊都沒有別的高樓的話
You can't see the uniqueness of this building
你反而看不出這個樓有什麼獨特性
where is he high
和高在哪裡
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
Thanks to this long article by Du Congming
由於杜聰明的這篇長文
Long essays up to 60,000 words
長到六萬字的長文
It should be the entire Japanese occupation period
應該是整個日治時期
even postwar Taiwan
甚至戰後台灣
rare heavyweight scientist
很少見的重量級的科學家
An important document for Chinese medicine and Chinese medicine
對於漢醫藥和中醫藥的一個重要文獻
so for me
所以對我來講
A big challenge is to say
一個很大的挑戰就是說
How do I find points to compare
我怎麼樣找到可以比較的點
so that we can compare
以至於我們可以比較來了解
His uniqueness and where his ideas lie
他的獨特性和他的想法所在
So the middle part of the speech below
所以這個演講的下面的中間的部分
all i want to do is
我想要做的就是
I want to put it in multiple historical contexts
我想把它放在多重的歷史脈絡下
Let everyone understand his possible uniqueness
讓大家來了解他的可能的獨特性
The first is to put it in Japan
第一個是把它放在日本
In the context of Japan
日本的脈絡下
The second is to put it in the context of Chinese and Western theory of truth in the period of the Republic of China
第二是放在民國時期的中西論真的脈絡下
just mentioned
就是剛剛提到的
Third I'm going to put it in
第三我要把它放在
In the context of the development of Western medical history
西方醫學史的發展的脈絡下
Especially an experimental therapeutic novelty
特別是一個實驗治療學的新奇
Another Chinese medicine hospital that he mentioned
另外一個他所提上的漢醫醫院
finally i called juicing
最後我叫突出
There is a very clever research method
有一個很聰明的研究方法
There is also a very unique place
也有一個很獨特的地方
I call it the reverse method of research
我稱之為道行逆施的研究法
Later I will explain from these five directions
待會我就會從這五個方向來說明
its special place
它特殊的地方
The first is Japanese
第一個是講日本
modernity with hygiene
與衛生的現代性
many friends know
很多朋友都知道
Japan began to accept the West
日本開始接受西方
The starting point of Western scientific case knowledge
西方科學案知識的起點
Anatomy of Genpaku Mita
就是三田玄白解剖
The right one he can't understand at all
對的一個他根本看不懂的
Dutch Anatomy Book Anatomy
荷蘭解剖書解剖
The structure of the human body as taught by Chinese medicine
這件漢醫所講的人體結構
It's all wrong, right?
全都錯了對不對
So he started working hard to learn Dutch
所以他開始發奮學荷蘭文
Then translate this book into Japanese
然後把這本書翻譯成日文
It becomes the dismantling new book
變成解體新書
This also became the starting point for the Japanese to become interested in blue studies
這也成為日本人開始對藍學有興趣的起點
Published in 191774
出版在191774年
this is a very early period
這是個非常早的時期
And let's just talk about it
而且大家光講這一點來看
know Japan's experience in medicine and medical science
就知道日本對於醫療和醫學科學的經驗
In contrast to China
跟中國剛好形成對比
So in the Opium War
所以在鴉片戰爭
Didn't China's self-improvement movement also start to introduce blood sucking?
中國的自強運動不是也開始引入吸血嗎
But at that time they didn't think
可是那時候他們完全不認為
Medicine is a particularly important science
醫學是一個特別重要的學問
In fact China began to accept medical
事實上中國開始接受醫學
Far more than it accepts chemistry, mining and other knowledge
遠遠於它接受化學、礦學等其他學問
until the beginning of the 20th century
一直到20世紀初
Manchuria became a transfer point only after it belonged
滿洲屬於之後才成為轉類點
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
Japan's acceptance of blood-sucking experience is in sharp contrast with China
日本接受吸血經驗跟中國形成強烈的對比
The starting point of Japan is related to medical anatomy
日本一開始的起點就跟醫療解剖學有關
And later the Japanese enlightenment master Fukuzawa Yukichi
而後來日本的啟蒙大師福澤玉吉
The school he himself originally attended was also the school run by Lan Yi.
他自己本來念的學校也是藍衣開的學校
If you read his biography now,
大家現在如果讀他的字傳的話
You'll see him with the students who were there at the time
你會看到他跟當時在那個地方的學生們
Let's take the opportunity to look forward to the former Han doctor
大家一起機朝以往以前的漢醫師
I think they are very unscientific and outdated
就覺得他們非常的不科學、非常的落伍
in other words
換句話說
Contemporary Japanese Enlightenment Master
當代日本啟蒙大師
his own enlightenment experience
他自己的啟蒙經驗
It's just that traditional medicine is wrong
就是傳統的醫學是錯的
should be discarded
是應該被揚棄的
And the more progressive development of this meaning
而且這個意義更進步的發展
That is to say, to become not only
就是說成為不僅成為
It became an important part of Japan's self-belief that it entered the modern era later.
成為日本自我認為後來進入現代的一個重要的
Medicine has become an important way for Japan to successfully join the West and modern times
醫學成為日本自己覺得成功的加入西方和現代的一個重要的途徑
And it also became a later combined with the colonial policy
而且也成為了一個後來也跟殖民政策結合
This is a classic work of our Asian studies
這是一個就是說我們亞洲研究的一個經典作品
hygienic modernity
叫衛生的現代性
It is pointed out in this work
這個作品中就指出說
It later became the core strategy of Japan's colonial expansion to Korea, Manchuria, Taiwan and China
後來成為日本殖民擴張到朝鮮滿洲台灣跟中國的核心策略
is not only a core experience of Japan
就是不僅成為日本的一個核心的經驗
And it became an important means of later colonial expansion
而且成為後來殖民擴張的一個重要的一個手段
so that we later heard that
以至於我們後來聽到就是說
Goto Shinpei
像台灣的民政長官後藤新平
It is also one of the very important promoters
也是其中一個很重要的推手
Then wrote the National Sanitation Principles
然後寫了國家衛生原理
It is also the close connection between medical care and hygiene
也是把醫療跟衛生密切的
Closely integrated with the governance of the country and colonial governance
跟國家的治理殖民的治理緊密的結合
And this is actually felt by people in the colonies
而且這個事實上是殖民地的人都可以感覺到的
So on New Year's Day in 1925, Taiwan's Ming Pao editorial
所以到了1925年的元旦台灣明報的社論
After 30 years of Japanese occupation, he said
日治30年之後他說
We are now looking back at the achievements of the Governor-General in the past 30 years
我們現在回顧總督治台30年的政績
Our most commendable from beginning to end
從頭到尾時我們最可稱讚的
It's about sanitary facilities.
便是衛生方面設施這一點吧
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
This is a stronger
這是一個更強烈的
That is to say, Du Congming is in the context of Japan
就是說杜聰明在日本的脈絡下
should be more strongly affirmed
應該會更強烈的肯定
Western Medicine and Hygiene
西方的醫學和衛生
And it's of very high importance to his
而且對他的有非常高的重要性
Du Congming is indeed so
杜聰明的確如此
He himself is not only a product of this
他自己不僅是這個產物
And therefore he thinks that
而且也因此他認為說
implemented in Taiwan
在台灣所推行的這個
The Doctrine that Let Han Physicians Dissolve Naturally
讓漢醫師自然解滅的主義
It is a policy that is extremely adapted to the requirements of the times
是一個極為適應時代要求的政策
He is sure of this policy
他是肯定這個政策的
That Japanese
那剛剛那個日本跟
Part of Modern Medicine and Hygiene
現代醫療和衛生的部分
You may be more familiar
大家可能比較熟悉
What you may not be familiar with is that
大家可能比較不熟悉的是說
What about the other side?
另外一面呢
Beginning to recognize in modern Japan
在日本近代開始認定
While Dr. Han was wrong
漢醫師錯誤的同時
But they have a
可是他們對本草卻有一個
very different history
非常不同的歷史
Only recently came out two recent books stating that
最近才出了 最近的兩本新書指出
After Materia Medica Okaki was introduced to Japan
在本草岡木傳入日本之後
Indeed Japan developed very close to modern natural history
確實的日本發展出十分接近現代自然史
Natural History
Natural History
Darwin was a natural history scholar, right?
達爾文就是一個自然史的學者 對不對
That is to say, beyond the tradition of traditional herbal medicine
就是說超越了傳統的本草的傳統
And the beginning equals that Japan is somewhat self-sufficient
而開始等於日本有點是自足的
developed a research tradition close to a natural history like Darwin's
就發展出了一個接近於像達爾文的那樣一個自然史的研究傳統
and developed a realistic image
而且發展出了一種寫實主義的圖像
That is to say, so at that time it was
就是說 所以在那個 到了是
Just like the pictures on the poster I gave you today, there are many
就像今天我給大家海報上的圖 有非常多
Everyone knows that the picture of Materia Medica Okagi does not have marble needles attached at all.
大家知道那個本草岡木的圖 根本理石針就沒有附
As far as the picture is concerned with Materia Medica, it has always been very crude
就圖對本草而言一直都是非常簡陋的
But we see very beautifully in the Japanese tradition
可是我們在日本的傳統中看到非常精美的
very close to our modern graph
很接近我們現代的圖
And this is combined with realism
而且這跟寫實主義也與以結合
Then this becomes a very important self-identity in the development of Japanese science
那這個成為就是說日本科學發展中的一個很重要的一個自我認同
It is through this that they are almost independent
就是他們透過這個等於是幾乎獨立的
independently developed their scientific traditions
自主的發展出他們的科學傳統
and not only in natural history
而且不僅是在自然史上
Later, this herbal tradition means
這個本草傳統到後來就是說
Changjing Changyi
長景長義
It is the founder of modern Japanese medicine
它是日本現代藥學的開山族
That's also the discoverer of ephedrine.
那也是麻黃素的發現人
So it is equal to this one of the University of Tokyo, Japan
所以等於日本東京大學的這個
Founder of the Department of Pharmacy
藥學系的開山祖師
He is based on the research on crude drugs of Chinese medicine
他就是建立在對漢藥的生藥研究上
And he was the one who extracted the ephedrine first.
而且是麻黃素最先把他萃取出來的人
That
那
Du Congming himself studied at Kyoto University
杜聰明自己在京都大學讀的
also a doctor of pharmacy
也是藥學博士
His teacher is also a master of pharmacy
他的老師也是藥學大師
So all this means
所以這些都說明就是說
After combining with this herbal medicine in Japan
日本在跟這個本草結合之後
developed not a total negation
發展出並不是一個全然的否定
But on Materia Medica and modern science
而是對本草與現代科學
have a deep bond
有一個深入的結合
So Du Congming said
所以杜聰明說
Japan since the Meiji Restoration
日本自從明治維新以後
Scientific research on the crude drugs of Galaxy
對河漢生藥的科學研究
Make the greatest contribution to the world
對世界有最大的貢獻
So everyone hear here
所以大家聽到這裡為止
might feel like saying
可能會覺得說
Du Congming's words sound like
杜聰明這句話說得好像
very simple
很簡單
But in fact, this sentence means more than we
可是其實這句話意義比我們
than he said
比他講的
He is too humble
他是講的太謙虛了
Because it sounds like you might just think that
因為這樣大家聽起來可能只是覺得說
Japanese for Materia Medical
日本人對於Materia Medical
Herbal research is better
本草的研究做得比較好
So just contribute the most in the world
所以在世界上貢獻最大而已
Not only that
其實不只是如此
When it comes to the era we are talking about now
等到到了我們現在講的這個時代的時候
In fact, modern western medicine
事實上西方現代藥學
don't think at all
已經根本完全不認為
in traditional herbal
在傳統的本草中
can find something worth researching
可以找到什麼值得研究的東西了
and it starts early
而且這很早就開始
The one on the left is a professor at Harvard University
左邊的這個是哈佛大學的教授
professor of medicine
醫學系的教授
In 1870 he said
他在1870年的時候他就說
If we take all Materia Medical
如果我們把所有的Materia Medical
If you throw them all into the sea
都丟到海裡去的話
humanity has nothing to lose
人類也沒有任何損失
It just might kill the fish
只是可能會害了魚而已
In other words, Materia Medica
換句話覺得本草
no research value at all
完全沒有研究的價值
the man on the right
那右邊這個人
This is what it was like in 1870
這是1870年的情形
By 1924
到了1924年
This man's name is John Grant
這個人叫John Grant
he is beijing
他是北京
Founder of Public Health Department of Xiehe Hospital
被協和醫院公衛系的創始人
Often referred to as the father of public health in China
一般被稱之為中國的公共衛生之父
He is also a famous hero in public health
也是公共衛生裡的一個著名的Hero
That is to say, it affects later
就是說影響到後來就是
that
那個
Let me not go too far
我先不要講太遠好了
He was sent to Union Hospital
就是他被協和醫院
When sent by Rockefeller's foundation to visit Japan
被洛克菲的基金會派去訪問日本的時候
He saw that Chinese medicine research is being done everywhere in Japan
他看到日本到處都在做漢藥研究
He felt very backward
他就覺得非常的落後
Then criticize the study
然後痛批這個研究
That's why I want to tell you that
就是所以我想跟大家講的是說
If we take time back to this era
我們若把時間拿回到這個時代去
What Du Congming said
杜聰明講的這句話
is too modest a statement
是一個太謙虛的說法
As far as Japan was not only affected by Japan at that time
就日本在當時不僅受到日本
The influence of German pharmacy
德國藥學的影響
make a great contribution
做出很大的貢獻
And this contribution was at the time
而且這個貢獻在當時
From an American point of view
從美國人的角度來看
It's an outdated and weird one at all.
根本就是一個落伍的很奇怪的
Why do you remember to study this
為什麼你還記住研究這種
worthless research
沒有價值的研究
and therefore
也因此呢
So like I just told you
所以像我剛剛跟大家講到
When we arrived at Peking Union Medical College Hospital
我們到北京協和醫院的時候
What about the Union Hospital at that time?
這個協和醫院當時呢
just to say
就是要表示說
I'm going to show you the Union Hospital
我要給你看叫做協和醫院
Now it was called John Hopkins in China
現在當時叫做John Hopkins in China
Rockefeller's Foundation
就是洛克菲的基金會
to make a concrete proof
要做一個具體的證明
building a genetic body
建立一個基因的機構
Let you know what is scientific research
讓你知道什麼叫科學研究
So everything is a parody of John Hopkins
所以一切都是模仿John Hopkins
only two things are not
只有兩件事情不是
one thing is his roof
一個事情就是他的屋頂
that is, they feel
就是說他們覺得要
since here
既然來這邊
I can't teach you everything
不能全部都是我教你
to show my respect for you
要表達一點我對你的尊敬
That's why we put a Chinese roof
所以才放一個中式的屋頂
Then this became the later
那這個也就成為了後來就是說
Characteristics of Chinese Modern Architecture
中國現代建築的特徵
Now you go to Beijing and see a lot of big roofs
你現在到北京看到很多有個大屋頂
And many people now feel that this is very
而且很多人現在覺得這很
What is not ideal is related to this development system
不理想的就是在跟這個發展系有關的
Another Rockefeller Foundation
另外一個洛克菲的基金會
There was a lot of internal debate at the time
當時內部辯論多時的
is whether they want to set up a
就是他們要不要成立一個
Department of Pharmacy to study Materia Medica
藥學系來研究本草
Which means they are very reluctant to do this research
就是說他們非常不願意做這個研究
but they say they come here
但他們說他們來到這裡
Everyone says they think there's a gold mine in there.
大家都說認為裡面有金礦
So there's a really big debate among them
所以他們內部有非常大的辯論
everyone can know
大家就可以知道說
You can imagine what Du Congming said just now.
可以想像剛剛杜聰明講的情況
What a unique situation at the time
在當時是多麼獨特的一個狀況
Definitely not to say that everyone is researching
絕對不是說大家都在研究
And very important is a unique influence of Japan
而很大重要是日本獨特的一個影響
Then some interesting history developed here.
那後來這邊發展出了一些有趣的歷史
But I don't want to go far
但我現在先不要走遠
I just want to come back and say something
我只要回來講一點就是說
I do an interpreted result
我這樣做一個解釋的結果
Explain that some friends will think that
說明有朋友會認為說
what you say
你這樣講的話
you've solved it
這你已經解完了
It is Du Congming who can do research and medicine
就是杜聰明會做要研究和醫藥
Just because it's a product of Japanese tradition, right?
就因為它是日本傳統的產物 對不對
Do you feel this way
大家是否有這種感覺
largely
很大程度上是
but if so you can't explain
可若是的話你就不能解釋
Then why does it suggest
那為什麼它的建議
The Governor's Palace has never accepted it, right?
總督府一直不接受呢 對不對
so I largely
所以我在很大程度上
What I want to say in this paragraph is to say
我在這一段我要講的是說
to a very large extent
在非常大的程度上
Du Congming proposed this research
杜聰明提出這個研究
It is indeed a product of Japan
的確是日本的產物
and at the time
而且就當時來講
is a very unique research tradition
是一個非常獨特的研究傳統
But our riddle isn't over yet
可是我們的謎還沒有解完
because if so
因為若是這樣
what he does is he is
他做的事就是他在
Easy to learn with the scene
跟場景長易學的
it's him
就是他在
words learned in college
大學學的話
That's no reason why he can't continue in Taiwan
那沒有理由他在台灣沒辦法繼續做下去
right
對不對
So I haven't solved my name yet
所以我這名字還沒有解完
then I'll go to another place first
那我先轉到另外一個地方
Said to put him in the second vein
說把他放到第二個脈絡裡
That's the one
就是那個
On the Truth between China and the West in the Republic of China
民國時期的中西論真
A very in the period of the Republic of China
一個非常在民國時期
Very comparable to Du Congming
非常可以跟杜聰明來相比的人
He is the super sinner in the history of Chinese medicine
是中醫史上的超級大罪人
Is Yu Yan
就是余言
This man is a graduate of a university in Osaka
這個人他是畢業於大阪的一科大學
Then in 1929 when he
然後他在1929年的時候
It was the first committee of the National Government to establish the Ministry of Health.
就是國民政府成立衛生部的第一屆委員會議社
Raise waste paper for medical treatment
提出廢紙就醫
To remove obstacles to medical hygiene
以掃除醫事衛生之障礙
like this case
像這個案子
Very big teacher plagiarized Japan
非常大程老師抄襲日本
Just to waste paper traditional medical treatment
就是要廢紙傳統的醫療
detonated the theory of truth between China and the West
就引爆了中西的論真
wait until after 1949
等到1949年之後
that is
就是說
because of this whole thing
因為這個整個事情
he plays a very important role
他扮演非常重要的角色
So after 1949
所以到1949年之後
After Mao Zedong began to support Chinese medicine
就是毛澤東開始支持中醫之後
TCM Policy During the Nationalist Government Period
整個國民政府時期的中醫政策
are called an oppressive Chinese medicine
都被稱之為一個壓迫中醫
Pneumonia Pneumonia Pneumonia Drug Storage Policy
肺炎的肺炎的肺炎存藥政策
So he alone represents the entire force of oppression
所以他一個人代表了整個壓迫的勢力
so this is a
所以這是一個
People who are often mentioned in the history of modern Chinese medicine
就現代中醫史裡經常為提到的人
Then he and Du Congming actually have a lot of similarities
然後他跟杜聰明其實有非常多的相近的地方
They also study in Japan
他們同樣留學日本
And there are people in Japan
而且在日本是有人
Du Congming's memoir video mentioned more than once
杜聰明回憶錄影不止一次提到過
pneumonia
肺炎
And then they also advocate the study of medical history
然後呢他們同樣都提倡研究醫學史
And almost at the same time sparked debates about traditional medicine
而且幾乎在同一個時間引發關於傳統醫療的論真
Du Congming was from 1928 to 1929
杜聰明是1928到1929
Fisherman is the spring of 1929
漁人是1929的春天
They also oppose the theory of Yin-Yang and Five Elements
同樣都反對陰陽五行學說
and both advocate the scientific approach to the study of traditional medicines
而且同樣都倡導以科學方法研究傳統藥物
As you can imagine, it's only natural
大家可以想像這是很自然的
Based on the Japanese tradition I just mentioned, right?
以我剛剛講的日本傳統對不對
But there is one big difference between the two
可是他們兩個有一個很大的不同
It is the fisherman who advocates the preservation of lung medicine
就是漁人主張肺醫存藥
and the fisherman said
而且漁人說呢
During the Republic of China
在民國時期
People who are eligible for research do not want to study traditional Chinese medicine
夠得上研究條件的人不想研究中藥
why
為什麼呢
because
因為
If we follow the American tradition we just talked about
如果按照我們剛剛講的美國傳統
Nogfi's genetic society is unwilling to try to study it
諾格菲的基因會都不願意嘗試來研究了
Then you're a really top-notch trained man
那你真的受過一流訓練的人
Why study this one people think is a Dying Science
為什麼要研究這一個人們都認為一個Dying Science
right
對不對
So everyone is unwilling to study
所以大家都不願意研究
However, many Chinese medicine practitioners say that they need to study
可是呢 很多中醫師都說他們要研究
But they don't have a laboratory at all, they don't have the ability
可是他們根本沒有實驗室 沒有能力
They are not eligible for research
他們構不上研究的條件
That's what Yu Yan said
那這是余言所講的
From this point of view
那從這角度來講
Du Congming constitutes an exception to what Yu Yan said
杜聰明就構成了余言所說的一個例外
Du Congming undoubtedly has the qualifications for research
杜聰明毫無疑問的有研究條件
And he is serious about studying traditional Chinese medicine
而且他還很認真要研究中藥
Not only does he want to study traditional Chinese medicine, but also his research methods
不僅他要研究中藥 而且他的研究方式
It's not about saving money
還不是費醫存藥
Have a public talk with Du Congming
與杜聰明有公開的說
I am a pharmacologist
我身為一個藥物學者
Mainly, of course, drug research
主要當然是藥物方面的研究
It's just that this plan also hopes to consider
只是這次計畫也希望能考慮
systematically carry out non-pharmacological
有系統的進行藥以外的
Research on Chinese Medicine
漢醫學的相關研究
And it is also surprising to say that
而且另外很令人吃驚的是說
The words written by Du Congming are often very
杜聰明寫的文字其實常常是非常
The step-by-step writing method that reveals the truth
揭實的步步為營的寫法
But he would jump out and say
可他居然會跳出一句說
I dare not say anything about the advantages and disadvantages of Chinese medicine and Western medicine
關於漢醫跟西醫的優劣我不敢斷言
only in the case of bone setting
只有在接骨這件事上
I dare say bone setting is much greater than western surgery
我敢說接骨要比西方的外科偉大多了
So Du Congming seems to be interested in Chinese medicine, including bone setting and snake medicine
所以杜聰明仿佛對於漢醫包括接骨和蛇藥
a lot of further knowledge, right?
有很多進一步的知識 對不對
So from this perspective, it is quite different from the language.
所以這個角度來講他跟語言也相當的不同
Now let me come back to the unresolved issue I just said about Japanese tradition
那我現在回來到我剛剛講日本傳統是沒有解開的問題
I said he is very much a product of Japanese tradition
我說他非常大程度上像是日本傳統的產物
But if that's the case, we can't understand
可如果這樣的話我們就沒辦法理解
Why has his ambition never been supported?
為什麼他的志向一直都得不到支持
That's because in that sense
那就是因為在那個意義上來講
Not a product of Japanese tradition
不是日本傳統的產物
To the third one, I will talk about the development of modern medicine, experimental therapeutics
到第三個我講現代醫學的發展實驗治療學
Du Congming in 1928
杜聰明在1928年
After he was sent by the Governor's Mansion to study in Europe and the United States for two years and four months, he came back
他被總督府送出去歐美留學兩年四個月回來之後
Written by European and American medical inspection talks
寫的歐美醫學視察談
He just talked about the results of his study tours in various places over the past two years.
他就講說他去這兩年多去各地留學考察的結果呢
He found that therapeutics is an independent lecture in universities in Europe and America
他發現在歐美的各大學治療學是獨立的講座
80% especially in France
佔80% 法國尤其如此
But in Japanese therapeutics
但在日本治療學
no individual lectures yet
還沒有獨立的講座
So when I say it, everyone thinks it's weird
所以我一講大家都覺得很奇怪
In fact, the Japanese medical system
事實上日本的醫學系統
Take Xi, Japan and Germany as a model
以習日以德國為模範
Only import the unique German medical tourism
僅輸入德國獨特的藥旅學
Therapeutic lectures that the French system says are very progressive
法國系統說很進步的治療學講座
no
就沒有
So from this point of view
所以呢從這角度來講
Du Congming, he is now going to propose
杜聰明他現在要提出
When experimental therapeutics is used to study Chinese medicine
實驗治療學來研究漢醫藥的時候
It was not a natural extension of his studies at Kyoto University
這不是他在京都大學研究的自然延伸
but his newly learned
而是他新學到的
Newly learned what I just learned in Europe and the United States
新學到在歐美剛剛學到的
The result of hitting the oil
撞油的結果
And we can see clearly from where he hit the oil
而且我們可以從他撞油的地方清楚看到
because the founder of experimental therapeutics
因為實驗治療學的創始者
Rockford
就是洛克佛
Chair of the Department of Pharmacy at John S. Hopkins University
John S. Hopkins大學藥學系的這個系主任
He organized the American
他呢組織了美國的這個
Society of Pharmacy and Experimental Therapeutics in 1908
藥學和實驗治療學的學會在1908年
Du Congming used to go to his laboratory when he hit oil
杜聰明在他撞油的時候曾經去他的實驗室
and say
而且說
This is one of the three American scientists he most admires
這是他最景仰的三位美國科學家之一
so from here
所以從這個地方
Everyone read his article
大家看他文章裡
In fact, he repeatedly proposed that experimental therapeutics
其實他反覆的提出實驗治療學
Rather than talk about medicine in general
而不是空泛的講 藥學而已
Not about animal experiments, not about chemical research
不是講動物實驗 不是講化學研究
It is about experimental therapeutics combined with clinical human research
而是講要結合臨床人體研究的實驗治療學
So it's not about him
所以這件事情並不是他在
Achievements of Learning at Kyoto University
京都大學學習的成果
And, wait until he is going back to Taiwan
而且呢 等到他要回台灣前
He just wrote that he thought of two things that could be done with experimental therapeutics
他就寫說 他想到兩項可以用實驗治療學
Study available in Taiwan
來在台灣可以進行的研究
One is the de-addiction treatment of duck slices
一個是鴨片的除癮治療
The second is the experimental therapeutics of traditional Chinese medicine
第二個就是漢醫藥的實驗治療學
So neither of those are direct extensions of his training in Japan.
所以這兩者呢 都不是他在日本訓練的直接延伸
And we can see that that is
而且我們這樣可以看到就是說
Two of his three famous studies relate to his latest learning
他有名的三個研究 有兩個都跟他最新學到的
Experimental Therapeutics Related
實驗治療學有關
And he is and we can see from today
而且呢 他這 而且我們從今天可以看得出來
He advocated this study
他提倡這個研究
Not only for the study of traditional Chinese medicine
不僅為了要研究漢醫藥
to promote new research methods
而提倡新的研究方法
He is also for the development of experimental therapeutics in Taiwan
他也是為了在台灣發展實驗治療學
Development of therapeutics that did not exist in the Empire of Japan at that time
發展在日本帝國裡當時還沒有的治療學
and self-transformation as an experimental therapist
而且自我轉型為實驗治療學家
away from what he was supposed to learn
脫離他本來要學的
It is only because of his identity as a scholar that he deliberately chooses research topics with local advantages
學家的身份才刻意選擇了有本土優勢的研究題材
So what is his choice?
所以他這個選擇呢
It's actually a two-way
其實是一個雙向的
On the one hand, he chooses one that he thinks will be useful for research
他一方面選擇一個他認為有助於研究
Research methods of traditional Chinese medicine
傳統漢醫藥的研究方法
his new method
他新學的方法
On the other hand, this theme with local advantages
另外一方面這個有本土優勢的題材
Because Westerners don't come to do research like this, right?
因為西方人不會來這樣研究對不對
so be him again
所以又成為他
Became a force for him to introduce the experimental therapy case and transform himself into an experimental therapist
成為他引入實驗治療學案自我轉型為實驗治療學家的一個力氣
So this chooses this two-way
所以這個選擇這個雙向的
Not only for Chinese medicine but also for the development of science
不僅為了漢醫也為了發展科學
Well everyone knows that
那大家都知道的就是說
Du Congming imagined that he would return to Taiwan to do two things
杜聰明想像中他會回台灣做兩件事
Then there was a completely different development
後來有完全不同的發展
one is
一個是
Taiwan's Governor's Office was criticized by the Taiwan People's Party for the Japanese policy of duck slices
台灣總督府因為當時受到台灣民眾黨批評說日本人的鴨片政策
Quickly accepted Du Congming's idea
很快就接納杜聰明的想法
Established the Taiwan Roots Institute of the Governor-General of Taiwan
建立了台灣總督府的台灣根深院
So he used experimental therapeutics to do the duck filming thing
所以他用實驗治療學來進行鴨片處影的事
Immediately paid to achieve
馬上就付出實現
From the time he wrote this article
距離他寫這邊文章
in less than a year
不到一年
another one
可另外一個
Another one is to say
另外一個就是說
It has never been possible to study sweat medicine
用來研究汗藥是從來都沒有辦法實現
took a completely different path
而走上了完全不同的路
So from this point of view
那所以從這角度來講
You can now see a
大家現在已經可以看到一個就是說
develop
發展
and not just to study a new discipline
而且不只是要研究一個新的學科
Du Congming also said to establish a new research institute
杜聰明還說要建立一個新的研究機構
khan medical hospital
叫做汗醫醫院
That's what I said at the time
那這也是當時就說
the harshest criticism of his critics
批評他的人最嚴厲的批評
He said
他說
this must be evil
這一定是心懷不軌
If you want to study sweat medicine
你如果要研究汗醫
sweat medicine
汗藥
Then continue the original research method
那麼延續原來研究法
You just need to set up a pharmacology lab
你只要成立藥理實驗室就好
right
對不對
conduct animal experiments
進行動物實驗
why do you want a hospital
你為什麼要醫院
Since you want a hospital
你既然要醫院
That must be hoping to rebuild a
那一定就是希望重建一個
The two medical systems that confront each other between Khan and current medical care
汗醫和現在醫療對峙的兩個醫療體系
So this is one of his biggest criticisms
所以這是他受到一個最大的批評
But from Du Congming's point of view
可是從杜聰明的角度來講呢
That's what he learned by crashing
這也是他撞油才學到的東西
and reflects what other people don't understand
而且反映了其他人不了解
his heart
他的他的用心
Khan Medical Research Hospital
他所說的汗醫研究醫院
Primarily a research institution
主要是一個研究機構
Twenty beds will basically witness the specific kind of patients we need for our experimental therapy class research
二十張病床基本上會目擊我們實驗治療課研究上所需的特定種類的患者
do not accept any patients
不接受任何的患者
In fact, you can tell from his physical experience
事實上你看他的狀遊的經驗就知道
This is the same as when he was at the Rockefeller Institut in New York at the time
這跟他在當時紐約洛克菲勒Institut
Met the famous Japanese scientist Hideshi Noguchi who had a close relationship
遇到的日本的知名科學家野口英式有密切的關係
where the host of the rockefeller institute
在那裡洛克菲勒研究院的主持人
Create the Rockefeller Institut as a new research institution
把洛克菲勒Institut創造成一個全新的研究機構
According to a medical historian
根據一個醫學史家說的
At a time when most hospitals in the United States are still trying to get basic lab facilities
當美國大部分的醫院都還在設法取得基本實驗設施的時候
Simon Flexner is the director of the Rockefeller Genetic Society
Simon Flexner就是洛克菲勒基因會的director
presents an almost utopian vision
提出了一個近乎烏托邦的願景
Ultimately a hospital is a laboratory
終極而言醫院就是一個實驗室
So the criticism of Du Congming just originated
所以剛剛起源對杜聰明的批評
In fact, it happened to be what Du Congming wanted to surpass.
事實上剛好是杜聰明要超越的
He established a will with the goal of research
他建立一個以研究為目標的一個意願
The two are one and two two are one
這兩者一而二二而一
Then Du Congming said, I know none of you have heard of it.
然後杜聰明就說我知道你們都沒聽過
But this kind of hospital
但這種醫院
Does exist
確實存在
not only in new york
不僅存在於紐約
Also present at the School of Tropical Medicine in London
也存在於倫敦的熱帶醫學院
Also present at the affiliated hospital of the School of Tropical Diseases of the University of Hamburg
也存在於漢堡大學的熱帶病學校的附屬醫院
So it not only has to mention a new discipline
所以它不僅要提一個新的學科
it will have a new research facility
它要有一個新的研究機構
Then it is worth saying a little bit here, that is,
那這邊值得稍微簡單說一個就是說
Du Congmin wants to set up a Chinese medicine hospital
杜聰敏要設立漢醫醫院進行
Research on Experimental Therapeutics of Chinese Medicine
漢藥實驗治療學的研究
Actually very close to the same time
其實非常接近同一個時間
In the period of the Republic of China, the goals that doctors of traditional Chinese medicine strived for
在民國時期中醫師他們所爭取的目標
Because at that time people criticized you and said
因為那時候人家批評你說
The theory of Chinese medicine is unscientific, etc.
中醫的理論啊 不科學等等
They all already find it difficult to argue
他們都已經覺得很難辯論了
so they feel like
所以他們就覺得說
I'll go first and I don't want to have so many scientific and philosophical debates with you.
我先來 我不要跟你進行這麼多的科學跟哲學的辯論
Let's first prove clinically that we are curative
我們先在臨床上來證明我們是有療效
So they emphasize that the theory of Chinese medicine may not be scientific
所以他們強調說中醫的理論也許不符科學
But the treatment is really effective
但治療上確實有效
so as to continuously strive for the establishment of
從而不斷地爭取成立
Traditional Chinese Medicine Hospital
採用中醫療法中醫醫院
In fact, the Legislative Yuan has passed
事實上立法院曾經通過過
But later because of the relationship between the Sino-Japanese War
但後來因為中日戰爭的關係
there is no way to create
就沒有辦法建立
But this is indeed the traditional Chinese medicine doctor in the period of the Republic of China
但這的確是當時的民國時期的中醫師
There are also Chinese physicians in Japan who are simultaneously promoting the direction
還有在日本的漢醫師都同時在推動的方向
I hope to build a hospital
就希望能夠建立醫院
So now I'm at the last entry in the multiple histories
那現在我進入到多重歷史的最後一項
On the Research Method of "Tao Xing Adversity"
就《道行逆施》的研究法
Du Congming not only wants to introduce a new discipline
就杜聰明不僅要引進一個新的學門
Establishment of new research institutes
建立新的研究機構
And in terms of research methods and procedures
而且就研究方法上 程序上
He's also going to come up with something different
他也要提出一些不同的方法
He said that there are two methods for the research of Chinese medicine
他說就漢藥的研究有兩個方法
A first analysis of chemical active ingredients in the laboratory
一個在實驗室裡先分析化學的有效成分
Use the method of experimental pharmacology to find out its function and use it in clinic
以實驗藥理學的方法找救民其作用而用於臨床
He said another way
他說另外一個方法
We use prescriptions for sick people to drink
我們用藥方供病人服飲
Observing the clinical effect first
先觀察到臨床上所得的效果
Then moved to the research laboratory to investigate the active ingredients and their pharmacology
而後移入研究室追究有效成分及其藥理
a good way
一數良善方法
Then what he said sounds simple
那他這樣講的聽起來很簡單
Just to mention two methods
就只是提兩個方法而已
But if we put this back into the context of the Republic of China
可是如果把這個放回到民國時期的脈絡化
is a highly debated
是一個高度被辯論
A debate on research design that also slams
還抨擊的一個關於研究設計的辯論
Someone even invented a term called
甚至有人發明一個名詞叫
12345 and 54321
12345跟54321
how to say
怎麼說呢
is what they think
就是他們認為說
Standard research procedure is
標準的研究程序就是
you first need to know
你首先要知道
what are you researching
你居然在研究什麼東西
So you have to extract the active ingredients first
所以你要先萃取出其中有效成分
right
對不對
So at that time
所以當時呢
National government started
國民政府一開始
When deciding to conduct research on traditional Chinese medicine
決定要進行中藥研究的時候
The first is the establishment of the Chinese Medicine Research Office
最先就是成立中藥研究室
Put it in the Chemistry Department of the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
放在中醫院的化學所裡面
So a lot of research has focused on this step
所以非常多研究都集中在這一步
in chemical analysis
在化學分析
Many times the composition cannot be found
很多時候都找不到組成分
or found the components
或者找到組成分了
No legendary medicinal effect
沒有傳說中的藥效
So I've been stuck on the first level
所以一直都卡在第一階上
So at that time
所以當時呢
As far as many TCM practitioners and those who support them say
就很多中醫師和支持他們的人說
why don't we come
那為什麼我們不來
Do clinical research first
先做臨床研究
try it on a human
先在人的身上試
but at the time
可在當時來講
highly controversial
就有高度的爭議
At the time, this was criticized as violating medical ethics.
在當時來講這卻被批評說是違反醫療倫理
Just take some medicines that you don't even know the effects and toxicity of the medicines
就你拿一些根本就不知道藥效應毒性的藥
use it on people
隨便用在人們的身上
Even those who criticize Chinese medicine will quote Su Shi
甚至於呢就是批評中醫的人會引個蘇世
What Su Dongpo said
蘇東坡說的話
Su Dongpo said to study books, waste paper, study medicine and waste people
蘇東坡說學書廢紙學醫廢人
That is to say, if you want to learn calligraphy, you will need to use a lot of declarations
就是說你要學書法你會要用到很多宣旨
What about you who studied medicine?
那你學醫學的人呢
Because you don't know how poisonous it is
因為其實你不知道有多大毒
You must have ruined a lot of people
你一定廢了很多人
It even means that the name must be the one that kills the most
甚至於就是說名義一定是殺人殺最多的
we don't know
大家不知道而已
So this approach will be very criticized
所以這個做法會遭到非常大的抨擊
and it's not an accepted practice
而且也不是一個被接受的做法
So what Du Congming just said
所以杜聰明剛剛說的那個
The way he said it very plainly
說的他很平淡的說出來的方法
In fact, in this context
其實在這個脈絡下
is a highly controversial method
是一個高度爭議的方法
Moreover, Du Congming not only pointed out that this method
而且杜聰明不僅指出這個方法
He even specifically pointed out which drugs he felt were the most worthy of research.
他甚至有具體的指出他覺得最值得研究的藥物
he just said
他就說
For so far, there is no way to extract the active ingredients chemically
對於至今還沒辦法以化學方法抽出有效成分
But Du Cong has clinically
但杜聰在臨床上具有
Drugs that treat real diseases
實病治療效果的藥物
For example Bupleurum and Changshan for treating sadism
例如治療虐疾的柴胡和長山
be the first to conduct more sophisticated experimental therapeutic studies on them
當先試的對他們進行更為精密的實驗治療學的研究
Make sure the experiment works before going to the lab
確定實驗有效在轉到實驗室裡
Perform precision chemistry and biology experiments in reverse
逆向的進行精密化學和生物學的試驗
this is a very important question
這是十分重要的問題
So it's not only talking about
所以它不僅在講的
It is such a research method that was criticized at the time
就是這樣一個被當時批評的研究法
And maybe you will find it surprising that
而且也許大家會覺得意外就是說
Of the only two examples it cites
它所舉出來的唯二的例子中的
one of the long mountains
其中的一個長山
After 20 years it has been proven that there is
在20年之後被證明確實有
It does work
確實有療效
then this is
那這個就是
was in the 1940s
是在1940年代
by Chen Guofu who has no medical background at all
由一個完全沒有醫療背景的陳國夫
You may have heard of him
大家可能有聽過他
Chen Lifu
就他弟弟陳立夫
We are in almost every TCM
我們幾乎在每個中醫
Chen Lifu's calligraphy will be seen in the clinics of Chinese medicine practitioners
中醫師的診所都會看到陳立夫的書法
Since the period of the Republic of China
他們在民國時期以來
has always been a supporter of Chinese medicine
就一直是中醫的支持者
But has always been considered a cultural conservative
可一直都被當成是個文化保守主義者
support based on ideology
基於意識形態而支持
support
進行的支持
But Chen Guofu did
可陳國夫的確
led to a scientific experiment in the 1940s
曾經促成了一個在1940年代的一個科學實驗
And this experiment proves the effect of Changshan drug abuse
而這個實驗證明了長山劑虐的效果
So later this was published in the journal of Science
所以後來這個有發表在Science的期刊上
At that time, Chang Shan’s article was called
那時候長山這篇文章叫做
Nagayama New Anti-Military Drug
長山New Anti-Military Drug
So it's been proven
所以這是確實被證實過的
that result
那成果
Du Congming cited this example in 1929 with only two examples
杜聰明在1929年只舉兩個例子就舉到這個例子
but he's never been able to do it
但他從來沒有辦法做過
But it proved to be a real success in 1943
但在1943的時候被證明是確實成功的
and what is more important
而且更重要的是什麼呢
The results of this research by Gofu
成果夫的這個研究的結果
is a study that directly affected last year's Nobel Prize in Qing Hao v.
是直接影響到去年德諾貝爾獎的清昊訴的研究
wait until 1967
等到1967年
As you all know the story we hear now is that
就大家都知道我們現在聽到的故事就是說
The CCP used the Vietnam War for the needs of the war
中共在越戰中為了戰爭的需要
made a political decision
做了一個政治的決定
Launch mission 523, right?
發動523任務對不對
Then began to contribute to the final picture and found Qinghao again
然後開始促成了最後的圖又又找到清昊訴
can cause sadism
可以致虐疾
And won the Nobel Prize in 2015
而得到2015年的諾貝爾獎
This is the question we hear most about the history of science in China
這是我們大部分聽關於中國的科學史的問題
It's just that you only hear Chairman Mao's decision
就是你只有聽到毛主席的決定而已
But in fact, if we go back and look at his historical materials at that time
可是其實我們現在回去看他當時的史料的話
at the beginning of this decision
在這個決定的一開始
The first one in the research on Chinese medicine is Changshan
裡面關於中醫藥的研究中的第一個就是長山
It is because we already know that Changshan is effective
就是因為已經知道長山有效
So there are two consequences
所以有兩個後果
The first is to say
第一個就是說
In the past, people once suspected that Chinese medicine did not abuse people and start addiction again
以前的人曾經懷疑中醫根本就沒有虐人從頭乾癮
How can you find a medicine that works, right?
怎麼可能會找到有用的藥對不對
Wang Jinwei said so
王金偉就這樣說過
He said that I never believe that Chinese medicine can cure infectious diseases
他說我絕不相信中醫能夠治傳染病
But what?
可是呢
In Guofu's experience, we already know that there is indeed
在成果夫的經驗裡已經知道的確有了
Does that make you feel like saying
那是不是會使得你覺得說
probably there will be, right?
很可能還會有對不對
Since they have found an effective drug before
就他們既然以前曾經找到過一個有效的藥
Then it's likely they've discovered other medicines
那麼很可能他們還有發現其他的藥
So the initial research consisted of two parts
所以一開始的研究呢是兩個部分
One part is hoping to reduce the
一個部分是希望能夠減低服用長山所造成的
That is, serious side effects such as vomiting
就是說嘔吐等嚴重的副作用
on the other hand
另外一方面
Later, if the side effects cannot be reduced, a new drug will be found
後來副作用不能減少就找新藥
Finally found this Qinghaosu
最後才找到這個清好素
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講
One of the examples selected by Dolceville
杜聰明維爾選的一個例子中的一個
It's actually a valid example, right?
其實就是有效的例子 對不對
Moreover, this example directly inspires
而且這個例子還直接的啟發到
The current one is to say
現在的一個就是說
The result of such a major scientific research
這麼重大的一個科學研究的成果
While at the Tuyoyo Drasca Committee
在圖幼幼德拉斯卡委員會的時候
committee committee says
委員會委員會說
This may be the past 50 years
這或許是過去50年中
The development of the most important Syriputics
最重要的Syriputics的發展
he said maybe but
他說可能但是
as you can imagine
大家可以想像就是說
this is a very
這是一個很
This is a
這是一個
so this is a
所以這是一個
Just look at this situation
就是大家來看這樣的一個狀況
What about this period of history?
那這一段歷史呢
And what?
而且呢
And not only is Du Congming right
而且不僅杜聰明說對了
That's right, the medicine
說對了這個藥
And in fact Chen Guofu
而且事實上陳果夫
Only the process of finding this medicine
只找到這個藥的過程
It is very similar to what Du Congming said
也跟杜聰明說的方法很像
I wrote a long article on this
關於這點我寫過一篇很長篇的文章
It's almost a joke
這講起來幾乎是一個笑話
As far as Chen Guofu's original and most primitive way is to
就陳果夫原來最原始的做法就是
He took a visitor to his house
他把一個來他家的訪客
He just feeds him
他就直接給他吃
That's the man who got sadism
就那個人得了虐疾
He was cured later, he was very happy
他後來就治好,他就很高興
Then he was at the Central Political School in Chongqing
然後那時候他是在重慶的中央政治學校
It is the National Chengchi University in Taiwan today.
就是我們今天台灣的政大
He is still the provost
他還那當教務長
He taught them the people in the discipline
他就教他們訓導處的人
put them bdsm students
把他們得了虐疾的學生
Take this medicine for them all
通通為他們吃這個藥
Then it turns out the saddle bugs in their middle school are really down
後來發現他們中學裡的虐人蟲真的減少
He just set up a laboratory
他才去成立實驗室
so it's really a
所以這真的是一個
Experimental research on humans first
先在人體上做實驗的研究
and therefore later
也因此後來
Other guests criticize him when they come to see it
別的客人要來看了之後都批評他
That is to say, he is the life of Chaojian
就是說他是朝簡人命
And what?
而且呢
That is, this is actually a medical waste
就是這其實是學醫廢人
So he was criticized a lot
所以他遭到非常多的批評
he can't refute
他沒辦法反駁
He only said that others criticized me as 54321
他只說別人批評我是54321
I am the pervert
我是這個倒行逆施
he can't refute
他沒辦法反駁
But not only
可是呢不僅
Chen Guofu's successful case
陳果夫這個成功的case
It is parallel to what Du Congming said
跟杜聰明說的是平行的
there is one more important thing
還有一個很重要的事情
Let me tell you about this process in detail
這個過程我再跟大家說詳細一點
that is
就是說
The first step in 54321 is chemical analysis
54321的時候第一步是化學分析
but many people will say
可是很多人會說
To go further, you have to figure out first
更進一步你要先搞清楚
You should analyze which crude drug, right?
你就應該分析哪一個生藥對不對
So you're doing pharmacognosy research
所以你要進行生藥學的研究
know what is this long mountain
知道什麼是這個長山
so in other words
那所以換句話說
Not just 12345 should be 012345
不只是12345應該是012345
You first know what Changshan is
你先知道什麼是長山
to find the components
才能找到組成分
for animal experiments
才能進行動物實驗
But what?
可是呢
In Guofu's case?
在成果夫這個案子中呢
he didn't
他沒有進行
i just told you
我剛剛跟大家講
He went directly to the local
他就從直接去當地的
From today's pharmacy to buy medicine
從今的藥房去買了藥
Is it for the receptionist?
接待人的身上用對不對
Wait until it proves effective
等到用了證明有效之後呢
Re-establish a research laboratory
再成立研究室
Then find everyone to make herbal medicine
然後找大家來進行生藥
Chemistry Clinical Aspects of Research
化學 臨床各方面研究
Just wait until it's time to do research in reverse
就等到反過來做研究的時候
A surprising thing was found to be
發現一個令人吃驚的事情就是說
Suppose they start
假設他們一開始
If you do pharmacognosy research first
先做生藥學研究的話
what's your first step
你要做的第一步是什麼
That's what Du Congming said
就是杜聰明說的
Because Japan has the greatest contribution
因為日本有最大的貢獻
We're looking at Japanese scientific literature research
我們這邊要查考日本的科學文獻研究
right
對不對
that japan as early as
那日本早在
Japan is already here
日本早在這個
In 1827, the plant of this long mountain was found
1827年的時候就已經找到了這個長山的植物
The identity of the plant
植物的這個identity
in 1827
在1827年的時候
This youth achievement has been found
這個青人眾成就已經找到了
And since then, it has been followed and everyone believes
而且之後呢一直被沿襲大家都相信
Most of the scientists in the Republic of China
民國時期大部分的科學家
also follow this noun
也都是跟著抽這個名詞
It is believed that the plants of Nagayama originated from this
認為長山的植物源於這個
But because their research on Guofu this time is to do clinical work first.
可是因為他們這次成果夫的研究是先做臨床
So they later found out that
所以他們後來發現說
the long mountain that really works
真的有效的那個長山
Oh, that is to say, the Japanese have already found out about this research
哦,就是說這個研究日本人早就找到
But said he couldn't cure sadism
可是說他沒辦法治虐疾
That's because Guofu's story was done clinically first.
那可是由於成果夫的故事是先做臨床
Already know it works, right?
已經知道有效,對不對
So later found out that
所以後來發現說
It turns out that we are not using this medicine, not this plant
原來我們用的不是這個藥,不是這個植物
It's another ancient mountain
而是另外一個積古長山
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講呢
It's because you didn't use one two three four five
就是因為你沒有用一二三四五
So you know this knowledge is wrong
所以你知道這個知識是錯的
Do you understand what I mean?
大家了解我的意思嗎
So it was very scientific from the beginning
所以從一開始就非常科學
First come to the scientists and then check the
先來找科學家然後去查了當時的
latest scientific literature
最新的科學文獻
Otherwise, he couldn't find this long mountain
要不然就是他找不到這個長山
Because this Changshan is mainly produced in Japan and South Korea
因為這長山主要產於日本跟韓國
Otherwise, he really bought this Changshan
要不然就是他真的買到了這個長山
Then use it to prove the conclusion of the Japanese
然後去用了就會證明日本人的結論
There's just no cure for sadism
就是沒辦法治虐疾的
But because he immediately went straight to the local pharmacy to buy
可是因為他立刻就直接去當地買那個藥房
pharmacy bought medicine
藥房買到了藥
So it can be seen from this
所以由此可見
The local pharmacy knows what works, right?
當地藥房知道什麼是有效的藥對不對
And because he bought that medicine first
然後因為他先買那個藥
Conversely know it works
反過來知道有效了
I found it wasn't this plant
找回來發現不是這個植物
So he came to the conclusion that
所以他得到的結論就是說
The Japanese keep getting it wrong
日本人一直搞錯了
The Japanese say Hechangshan
日本人講的是河長山
It is different from Changshan in China
跟中國長山不一樣
That's the history we just had
那這是就是我們剛剛前面一段歷史
Materia Medica Research in Japan
日本進行本草研究
It is because some plants do not grow in Japan
就是因為有些植物日本不產
He looks for alternative plants
他找替代的植物
But I'm not going far now
但是我現在不要走遠了
just say a little bit
只要講一點就是說
In this case
以這個個案來講
This successful example is not only
這個成功的例子不僅是
not one two three four five
不是一二三四五
And we can conversely say
而且我們可以反過來說
It's because he's not one, two, three, four, five that he succeeds so quickly
就因為他不是一二三四五才成功這麼快
right
對不對
Otherwise, it would not be easy to succeed so quickly
不然還不容易成功的這麼快
so this is
所以這是
Another interesting point in this case
一個這個個案中另外很有趣的一點
So the story is actually more like
所以這個故事其實比較像是
Clinical application comes to a historical process of pharmacognosy research
臨床適用來到生藥學研究的一個歷史進程
ok so what?
好 那可是呢
Du Congming said lightly
杜聰明很輕描淡寫的就是說
this is also a good way
這也是好辦法
But in the period of the Republic of China to adopt this idea
可是在民國時期採取這種想法
Everyone is scolded to death
人都被罵得半死
can't defend myself
也不能為自己辯護
Like this doctor of traditional Chinese medicine, he said
像這個中醫師他就說
Regardless of any drug, first determine its principle from science
無論任何藥物先從科學確定他的原理
clinically validated
再從臨床驗證
The truth is very smooth, but it is difficult to fake it
道理很順 但作假很難
Know from clinical knowledge first, then go to principle from scientific verification
先從臨床知道再從科學驗證去原理
Prepare for troubles
與理不順而於事備益
That's a defense he barely makes
這是他勉強提出的一個辯護
But it's weak to say it, right?
可是說起來也是有氣無力的 對不對
So you can see that
所以大家可以看得出來就是說
The results are attached here
成果附在這邊
in the plain looking lexeme
在看起來很平淡的詞位中
He proposes a potentially highly controversial
他提出了一個其實可以有高度爭議
And it is not accepted by others
而且不被別人接受的做法
He has
他有
He is in a research project
他在一個研究計畫裡
To introduce a new discipline
要引進一個新的學科
create a new institution
建立一個新的機構
make another
再做一個
a new research method
一個新的研究法
There are just too many anomalies that challenge the original research paradigm
只有太多異常都挑戰了原來的研究典範
It's no wonder that you will be criticized by others
也無怪乎就說會遭到別人的批評
OK, so I'll put it in five veins now
好 那我現在把它放到五個脈絡
let's come back
就我們再回來看
It turns out that I was talking about the mystery of Du Congming's research
原來我講的杜聰明研究之謎
We can get an idea of ​​what
我們可以得到什麼樣的一個想法
That's why he continued his life promoting unscientific
就是為什麼他持續一生推動不科學的
What about research methods that are considered unscientific?
被認為不科學的研究法呢
From our point of view today
從我們今天這角度來看
It doesn't seem like he's promoting some unscientific research method
這似乎不是他在推動一個什麼不科學的研究法
Instead, a research approach with multiple breakthroughs
相反的是一個有多重突破的一個研究法
right
對不對
That means his research was indeed influenced by Japan
就是說他的研究的確受到日本的影響
Inspired by Japanese Pharmacy
受到日本藥學的啟蒙
but he introduced experimental therapeutics
但他引入了實驗治療學
To break through the tradition of no therapeutic research in the Japanese Empire at that time
來突破日本帝國當時沒有治療學研究的傳統
And it also broke through in the West
而且呢也突破了在西方
You have no tradition of using experimental therapeutics to study herbal medicine
你根本沒有用實驗治療學來研究本草的傳統
Both are breakthroughs
這兩個都是突破
Then you turned to the context of the Republic of China and spoke
然後你翻了民國的脈絡下來講話
He is a tall man that is to say
他是一個有高度的就是說
best scientific training but he chooses to do research like this
最好的科學訓練 但他就選擇做這樣的研究
Then he will introduce an East Asian
然後呢 他會引入一個在當時東亞
Unheard of idea for a research hospital
聞所未聞的一個研究性的醫院這個想法
Then came a highly controversial one
然後就提出了一個具有高度爭議性的一個
The Way of Doing the Right Way
道行逆施的研究法
And this research method was later proven to be effective, right?
而且這個研究法後來被證實是有效的 對不對
So from this point of view, even if there is no why puzzle
所以從這角度來講 就算是為什麼謎題都沒有
There is no way to untie it, I think at least everyone can
沒辦法解開 我想至少大家可以
One thing I feel is that he's definitely not an understatement when he mentions this whole project.
感覺到一件事就是說 他提這整個計畫絕對不是一個保守
or the traditional way
或者說傳統的做法
but a very forward looking
而是一個非常forward looking
That is to say, a breakthrough idea
就是說具有突破性的一個構想
I hope everyone can feel that this can be established
希望大家能夠覺得這點可以成立
That
那
And I can't help but want to say one more thing
而且我忍不住想要多說一句
maybe not directly related to puzzle solving
也許不直接跟解謎有關
That said, I think it's not only a pretty groundbreaking idea
就是說我覺得這不僅是一個很突破性的構想
It's actually a very strategic and ambitious idea
事實上也是一個非常具有策略性和雄心的構想
Because in many ways
因為在非常多的角度上來講
He was on the edge, right?
他當時都處於一個邊緣 對不對
In terms of modern medicine
如以現代醫學來講的話
He didn't have experimental therapeutics in Imperial Japan
他在日本帝國還沒有實驗治療學
compared to imperial japan
相對於日本帝國
Of course Taiwan is not a center of medicine
台灣當然也不是醫學的中心
Compared with traditional Chinese or traditional Chinese words
相對於傳統的漢裔或中醫的話
Of course also the center
當然也是中心
We will take it for granted that it is right in China
我們會當然認為在中國對不對
But he doesn't limit himself by fear of the edge
可是他並不以畏懼邊緣而自我限制
Instead he combines all the edges together
相反他把所有的邊緣組合在一起
and became a very groundbreaking idea
而成為一個非常突破性的想法
So after he combined these edge positions where they were originally located,
所以他把這些本來著處的邊緣位置組合之後
He can use the rigorous training and qualifications of scientists rarely seen in the Republic of China
他可以以民國時期罕見的科學家的嚴格訓練和資格
is the qualification
就是資格
Experimental Therapeutics was developed even after the Japanese Empire was established in Taiwan
在台灣建立起日本帝國都還帶發展的實驗治療學
Building and researching traditional medicine in East Asia that the Western world has not fully mastered
建研究西方世界尚未能充分掌飾的東亞傳統醫療
So if this thing is really done for him
所以如果這件事真的給他做得起來的話
He does have a unique trait, doesn't he?
他的確有一個很獨特的利績對不對
Hardly anyone is his main competitor
幾乎沒有什麼人是他主要的compatitor
I think it's a very ambitious
我覺得這是一個很有雄心
And I am very active in the idea of ​​combining my weaknesses into strengths
而且很積極在組合自己的弱勢成為優點的想法
at least to me
至少對我還覺得
It's very inspiring, so I want to share it with you.
蠻激勵的 所以跟大家分享一下
Well
那 好
If we start from this point of view
那如果從這個角度出發的話
We can have a few further questions
我們可以有幾個進一步的問題
One is why Du Congming has the value of traditional medicine
一個是 杜聰明為什麼對傳統醫藥的價值
have such deep appreciation
有這麼深入的賞識
to conceive of such a groundbreaking research project
以至於構想出如此具有突破性的研究計畫
Because everyone can feel it
因為大家可以 引然可以感覺得到
The reason why he wants to come up with so many breakthroughs
他之所以要想出這麼多的突破
There is a big reason
有一個很大原因就是
He believes in the value of traditional medicine more than
他相信傳統醫療的價值超過目前為止
The value of our research with pharmaceutical methods
我們用藥學方法研究的價值
right
對不對
He understands that
他明白的這樣講過
so what
那所以呢
Because he believes that there is such a value that far exceeds the current realization
因為他認為有這麼有遠超過目前實現出來的價值
He's the one who conceived of a breakthrough research project.
他才要構想突破性研究計畫
Why does he have such deep appreciation
他為什麼會有這麼深入的賞識
that's actually a good question
那其實這是個好問題
And this also involves the history of Chinese medicine in Taiwan
而且這也涉及到台灣中醫史的問題
But I can't tell you now
但我現在沒辦法跟大家
back back give complete answer
回 回 做完整的回答
but i think it's an interesting question
但是我想這是個很有意思的問題
what about the second one
那第二個呢
Everyone like just now if it sounds like after
大家像剛剛如果現在聽起來之後
should feel a little bit
應該會有點覺得
I think Du Congming now sounds
覺得說 杜聰明現在聽起來
Du Congming is a very normal scientist
杜聰明就是一個很正常的科學家
normal but ambitious scientist
正常而有野心的科學家
It's just a normal research project, right?
提出一個很正常的研究計畫而已 對不對
Then where is my Du cleverness fascinated?
那我的杜聰明致迷到哪兒何在
If everyone now thinks that I seem to cancel Du Congming to be fascinated
如果大家現在覺得我似乎取消杜聰明致迷的話
That is to say, our second question is to say
就是說 我們的第二個問題就是說
Why such a breakthrough research project
為什麼具有這麼突破性的研究計畫
still persists as a conservative
仍然持續的被視為一個保守的
Conservative and reactionary approach
保守反動的做法
Then I will now return to the main axis of our article
那我現在就回到我們這個文章的主軸
This is largely the same as what we just said
這很大的程度上就跟我們剛剛講的就是說
the Great Rupture of Modernity
現代性的大斷裂有關
That's why the so-called Du is clever and fascinated
就是 所以所謂的杜聰明致迷
In fact, it has nothing to do with Du Congming
其實跟杜聰明的關係不大
he is a normal scientist
他是一個正常的科學家
Just might suggest some more cutting edge
只是可能提出了一些更前沿
more challenging
更挑戰當時的
existing scientific research methods
既有的科學研究方法的做法而已
So let's put it
所以說呢 我們把它
If we think he's a fan
如果我們覺得他是個迷
words that can't even be played
甚至無法棋齒的迷的話
just reflects people's static view of science
只是反映了人們靜態的科學觀
especially regarding modern science and traditional medicine as two opposing
特別是把現代科學和傳統醫療視為兩個對立的
holistic view of science
水火不容的整體的科學觀
This is the atmosphere of the whole era
這正是當時整個時代的氛圍
even to some extent today
甚至到今天某程度上來講
are still the atmosphere of our time
都仍然是我們這個時代的氛圍
If I am wrong, please correct me, Vice President Liu.
我下面講如果不對請劉副院長糾正我
I heard
我聽說
I remember that academicians of Academia Sinica discussed it ten years ago
我記得好像十年前中研院士有討論過
Should Chinese medicine or Chinese medicine be an elective course in medical school?
要不要讓中藥或漢藥成為醫學院的選修課
It seems that the academicians object
好像院士們反對
Said that because the Taiwanese are superstitious enough
說因為台灣人已經夠迷信了
If the Academia Sinica takes the lead in incorporating this course into the teaching materials of the medical school
如果中研院在率先把這課納入醫學院的教材的話
Taiwanese will become more superstitious
那台灣人會變得更迷信
It's a sign that a problem is still alive
這還是一個問題仍然活著的象徵
right
對不對
That is to say, if today we cannot clearly distinguish
就是說如果今天我們不能夠很清楚分清楚
What is science, what is not science, what is tradition, what is modern
什麼是科學什麼是不科學什麼是傳統什麼是現代的話
if you don't know
你分不清楚的話
Then everything has to be examined and debated one by one.
那所有的事情都要一一檢視一一辯論
This political Du Congyuan first said what he didn't want to do
這政治杜聰明元先說他不要做的事
It's something the Fusni man said he wouldn't do.
是傅斯尼人說他不要做的事
He said it was very clear, right?
他說這事情很清楚了對不對
So from this point of view
所以從這角度來講呢
Our Great Rupture in Modernity
我們在現代性的大斷裂
If it can be established
能夠成立的話
must be very clear
就必須要很清楚分清楚
Who is scientific progress and who is conservative and reactionary
誰是科學進步 誰是保守反動
right
對不對
that way you can make a lot of decisions without doubt
那這樣你才能夠做很多決定而不會懷疑
don't say anything, you start to feel like saying
不會說動不動你就開始覺得說
This matter is not good for our situation in Taiwan.
這件事搞不好我們台灣的狀況
different from anywhere in the world
跟世界各地都不相同
then everything needs to be discussed
那就每件事都需要討論了
So under this big break in modernity?
所以在這個現代性的一個大斷裂之下呢
It's hard for you to tolerate thoughts like Du Congming's
你很難容得下像杜聰明這樣的想法
in his thoughts
他這樣的想法中
He is not only a representative of modernity
他不僅是又是現代性的代表
and he feels
而且他覺得
The value that exists in the tradition is worth learning
傳統中所存在的價值值得學習的東西
far beyond what we understand today
遠超過我們今天所了解的
so that we are worth developing
以至於我們值得發展
Some newer research methods
一些更新的研究方法
Even challenge the existing research methods
甚至於挑戰既有研究方式
to realize these values
來實現這些價值
That's exactly what it means
那這正是就是說
in those days or today
在當年或者是到今天
Many times we are not able to
很多時候我們都不能夠
accepted things
接受的事情
That
那
It is precisely because of the fact that Du Congming was included in the modernity discourse
正由於南以將杜聰明歸入現代性論述中
And one of the poles of our common sense
還有我們常識中的兩極之一
Therefore, Du Congming's research on Chinese Yi medicine
所以杜聰明的漢義藥研究
had to become a
才不得不變成一個
The mystery of unknown language
眾人視而不見 聽而不聞 語言不詳的謎
So I don't know if people will think that it means
所以我不知道大家會不會覺得就是說
We heard on the one hand that he had three studies
我們一方面聽說他有三個研究
But now if you go to see
可是現在大家如果去看
There are so many books about Du Congming
房間非常多關於杜聰明的書
Almost none of us have heard of the research on Chinese Yi medicine
我們幾乎都沒有聽過漢義藥的研究
right
對不對
Even if everyone mentions
甚至大家如果提起的時候
It's a bit embarrassing
還搞不好也覺得有點尷尬
And then and historically he has never been able to
然後而且歷史上他也從來沒有辦法
put it into practice
付諸實現
So from this point of view
所以在這個角度來講
This is such a very creative project
這個這樣一個非常富有創造性的計畫
It became impossible to realize back then
就變成當年沒辦法實現
And this year we have no way to incorporate the easy
而且今年我們也沒辦法把容易輕易的納入
He made a Taiwan medical modernity
他做一個台灣醫學現代性
or the image of the representative of scientific modernity
或科學現代性的代表人的形象之中
Putting it into this story seems to create a
放入這個故事中好像創造出一個
figuratively
形象上的
Maybe some people will think it's a stain
也許有人會認為是污點吧
That is to say, because of this, it becomes impossible for us to see this
就是說因此才會變成我們都沒有辦法看到這個
see him like this
看到他這個形象
Well, now I'm at the end of my speech.
好 那現在 我的演講到了最後了
I just started talking to you about a big issue that concerns me, right?
我剛一開始跟大家講的是一個我所關心的大問題 對不對
That is to say, how has Chinese medicine developed within half a century
就是說 中醫如何在半個世紀之內
From 1925 to 1997
從1925年到1997年
From the deadly enemy of modernity to the most concrete symbol and tool of Chinese exploration and modernity
由現代性的死敵轉化為中國探索及現代性最具體的象徵與工具
Then the example I gave you today is not an example in the context of China
那我今天給大家提供的例子並不是一個在中國的脈絡下的例子
But an example of a parallel correlation
可是有平行性相關性的一個例子
And then I by this case
然後我由這個個案呢
That said, let's say this is my main title
就是說 來說這是我的主標題
If we try to put the story of Du Congming into this historical transformation
我們現在試著把杜聰明這個故事放進這個歷史轉化之中的話
what would we think
我們會想到什麼
I think everyone would sometimes think about why this transformation happened.
我想本來大家有時候會想的時候 想為什麼會這個轉化
The easiest thing to think of is how many
最容易想到的就是有幾個
One is that China is very backward anyway, right?
一個就是說 反正中國就是很落後 對不對
So there has been no progress
所以一直都沒有進步過來
Even the original research results of the academic circles would think that
甚至於學界本來研究的成果會認為說
used by Mao Zedong
被毛澤東所利用
to claim a new China with a very different science
來宣稱一個新中國有一個非常不同的科學
So support TCM for political reasons
所以因為政治的理由而支持中醫
This is for academia
這對學界來講就是
before i wrote my book
在我寫我的書之前
This is the most popular saying
這是最流行的說法
That is to say, to explain this process of historical transformation in this way
就是說來這樣解釋這個歷史轉化的過程
But if we now
可是如果我們現在
Putting this historical course in the words of a smart story
把這個歷史過程中放進度聰明的故事的話
we added a lot
我們增加了非常多
such a parallel story
這樣一個平行的故事
In such traditional thinking
這樣的傳統想法中
elements that cannot be seen
沒有辦法看到的元素
For example, the Japanese medicinal tradition
譬如說日本的藥學傳統
right
對不對
that is
就是說
The process of historical transformation
這個歷史轉化的過程
It is related to the scientific development of Japan
跟日本的科學發展是有關的
This is not a story that happened entirely in China
這不是完全發生在中國的一個故事
and in fact in my book
而且事實上在我的書裡
There are also references to more Japanese influences
還有提到更多來自日本的影響
For example, in the late Qing Dynasty
譬如說在清末的時候
After all, it was already very bad.
真究本來已經很衰為了
Later, it was because Japan still kept the truth
後來就是因為日本仍然保留真究
That's why the reformers of Chinese medicine in the Republic of China said
所以民國時期的中醫的改造者才說
We should pull the truth back to the core of Chinese medicine
我們應該把真究重新拉到中醫的核心
become one of his four main axes
成為他的四大主軸之一
That's why it's 1971
所以才會有1971年的時候
That is to say, Restin went to China to discover the real situation
就是說Restin到中國發現真究的這個狀況
So there are scientific implications in this story
所以這個故事中有科學的影響
Also has Japanese influence
也有日本的影響
Second Experimental Therapeutics
第二 實驗治療學
this story is not a
這故事不是一個
It is a historical process with many new scientific developments
是有非常多跟新的科學發展的一個歷史過程
So people who try to support Chinese medicine
所以企圖支持中醫的人
Not all conservative and reactionary people
並不是都是保守反動的人
Instead, many of them want to bring in the latest
他們很多人反而想要引進最新
Introduce and seriously attempt to introduce the latest scientific developments
引進而且是認真的企圖引進最新的科學的發展
Come into this history and give him evidence
到這段歷史之中來給他證據
The third is that they don't even just import
第三 就是說他們甚至不只是引進
even in their environment
他們甚至於在他們所在的環境中
Attempt to create a unique local research method
企圖創造出當地的一個獨特的一個研究法
Of course, this will meet with great resistance.
那當然這會遭到非常大的阻力
Just like Du Congming's "Tao Xing Reverse Casting"
就像杜聰明提出來的《道行逆施法》
What about the fourth?
那第四呢
That is to say, the person concerned does have a value for traditional medical treatment.
就是說當事人的確有一個對傳統醫療價值
is a very deep understanding
是一個非常深入的領悟
Moreover, Du Congming mentioned Changshan
而且呢 杜聰明提到的就是長山
this specific drug
這個具體的藥物
What everyone wants to see is actually really surprising, right?
大家想見的是其實真正應該會滿驚奇對不對
He only lifted two pills and he lifted one
他只舉兩個藥 他就舉到了一個
Drugs that were later proven to be effective
後來被證明真正有效的藥
And this Changshan, although in Du Congming's story
而這個長山呢 雖然在杜聰明的故事中
He has been unable to bring this research to fruition
他一直沒辦法把這個研究付諸實現
Only one ideal is missing
只差了一個理想而已
And not only there is no way to realize it, but only an ideal
而且不僅沒辦法付諸實現 只一個理想
and in our history
而且在我們歷史上
We hardly even know about it
我們也幾乎都不知道這件事
But he's in another vein
可是他在另外一個脈絡中
parallel unrelated
平行的無關的
Chen Guofu has not read Du Congming's article
陳果夫沒有讀過杜聰明的文章
as far as i know no
就我所知是沒有
But after 1945, he had contacted Du Congming
但1945年之後他有跟杜聰明聯絡過
But the development of Changshan is independent of Du Congming
但長山的發展是獨立於杜聰明的
this suggested
這個建議的
It has been proven that it can indeed treat malaria
卻被證實的確可以治療虐疾
and even contributed to a
而且甚至於還促成了一個
major breakthrough in medicine
醫學上重大的突破
Qinghaosu
就得到諾貝爾獎的清好素
so i now
所以我現在
last say
最後講的意思說
I can't give you a story about this
我沒辦法給大家提供一個關於這個故事
complete conclusion
完整的結論
But if you take this story
但是如果大家把這個故事
put it in
放進來的話
We feel this transformation process
我們感覺到這個轉化過程中
Shouldn't just be entirely traditional
應該不只完全是傳統
right
對不對
It is not because Chinese medicine has always maintained a traditional situation
並不是因為中醫一直維持傳統的處境
And after this transformation
而經過這個轉化
On the contrary, he follows the trend of the modern system
相反的他跟現代的制度之勢
There is a lot of interaction
有非常多的互動交流
And what?
而且呢
But what about this history?
可是這段歷史呢
also full of creativity
也充滿了創造力
There are many people who think
有非常多人在心中認為
They know the value of traditional medicine
他們知道傳統醫療的價值
come up with creative ways
構想出具有創造力的方式
hope to confirm
希望能證實
In his example there is no way to achieve
在他例子中沒辦法實現
But here it is implemented
但在這裡卻實現了
Du Congming
然後在杜聰明
And it's important to
而且很重要一點是
such historical cases
這樣的歷史的個案
most of our time
在我們大部分的時候
When we think about this history
我們在想這段歷史的時候
almost completely invisible
幾乎都完全是而不見的
without entering our consciousness
就沒有進入我們的意識中
So the last thing I want to tell you is
因此我最後想跟大家說的是
The development of this history
這段歷史的發展
maybe more than we thought
也許比我們原來想的
a lot more interesting
還有趣的很多
And it is worth our deep thinking
而值得我們來深入的思考
that ends my report
那我的報告就到此結束
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you very much Dr. Lei for a very wonderful presentation
非常感謝雷博士非常精彩的演講
shall we be more open
那我們是不是開放一些
Is there anything I want to ask Dr. Lei?
有什麼想要請教雷博士的
Or some comments are welcome
或是有些comment歡迎提出來
Hello, teacher
老師你好
When I was in 2006
那個我2006年的時候
Graduated from National Taiwan University School of Medicine
從台大醫學院畢業
for new drug development
去做新藥開發
So about what you said ten years ago
所以關於你說的十年前
Academician of Central Plains
中原院士
Then they opposed Chinese medicine research
然後他們反對中藥研究
I remember this incident very clearly
這件事情我記得非常清楚
Because in fact, even National Taiwan University Hospital
因為其實就算是台大醫院
They probably lasted until 100 years
他們大概一直是到100年的時候
In the 100th year of the Republic of China
民國100年的時候
Only then did they really feel that doing Chinese medicine research
他們才開始真正覺得做中藥研
is valuable
就是有價值的
Before that in National Taiwan University Hospital
在那之前在台大醫院裡面
You said you want to do Chinese medicine
你說你想要做中藥
people will think
人家會覺得
think you are weird
覺得你很奇怪
right
對
so this thing is true
所以這件事情是真的
And about the perverse
然後關於那個倒行逆施的
It is Mr. Du Congming's perverse research method
就是杜聰明先生他倒行逆施的研究法
So I knew it when I was in the National Taiwan University Hospital
所以我也在台大醫院裡面的時候就知道
And then when I started doing medicine
然後當我開始去做藥的時候
At that time, Omics in the world was physical science
那時候是世界上Omics就是體學
Right technology started to develop
對 技術開始發展起來
Then don't say that you will be criticized at that time
然後你不要說在那個時候就會被批評
When we were making medicine
我們那時候在做藥的時候
what we are happy about is
我們很高興的就是
In the bamboo, you can buy the general clothes
竹裡面有買那個支普衣
Zhipuyi is theoretically a kind of
支普衣理論上是種
what do you put in
你什麼東西放進去
Then all his ingredients will be beaten out of the one
然後他所有成分都會被打出來的那一種
We are very happy to ask the senior
我們就很高興的問學長說
Hey, senior, why does the teacher only look at one component at a time?
欸 學長那為什麼老師一次只看一個成分
why didn't he say
他為什麼不說
Pull out everything in the tape sample you analyzed
你分析的帶樣品裡面的全部東西都拉出來看
Why would you take that Profi
為什麼你要把那個Profi
just as long as it's not this
就是只要不是這個
Delete all the medicines we want to see
我們要看的藥就把它通通都刪掉
But there might be something else very important in him
可是他裡面可能有其他很重要的東西
For example, it doesn't matter if he wears something
比方是他的帶些無所謂
Then I was scolded by the senior
然後結果我就被學長罵了
He said don't ask strange questions
他說你不要亂問奇怪的問題
You get punched every time you ask weird questions
你每次都亂問奇怪的問題才會被打出來
So I used to be scolded by the teacher
所以以前只是被老師罵
And then later when I left the State Department
然後後來當我離開國務院
Then when I went to the hospital to do clinical work
然後開始去醫院做臨床的時候
I found out that it's not just the teacher who scolds you
我發現會罵你的不只是老師
The teacher is more kind
老師還比較親切一點
you are IRB
你被IRB
When the human experimentation committee held the cannon accountable
人體試驗委員會追責炮的時候
that's the scariest thing
那才是最可怕的
but i think in fact
可是我覺得事實上
we should be able to say
我們應該可以說
The teachers of the Human Clinical Trials Committee
那些人體臨床試驗委員會的老師
he doesn't seem to understand
他好像不太理解
Is it the value of this matter?
到底是不是這件事情的價值在哪裡
So what you said, teacher
所以老師你說的這件事情
In fact, until now
事實上一直就算到現在
I think he is still in Taiwan
我覺得他在台灣都還是
keeps happening
持續的在發生
yes then that about
對 然後那關於
that traditional medicine
就是那個傳統醫學
Why is he fighting for this technology
他為什麼就是爭取這個技術
i remember i was in 2011
我記得我2011年
When studying Chinese medicine at Yangming University
在陽明大學學習中醫的時候
At that time, I was also very happy to learn to fight for
那時候我也很高興的想要學習爭取
But everyone says I don't have wisdom roots
可是大家都說我沒有慧根
Because it is not only people who can fight
因為就是不只人可以做爭取
you may find it difficult for you to study
你可能會覺得你很難學習
But not only people can fight
可是不只人可以做爭取
You can fight for the teacher
你可以對老師做爭取
But then this problem will come
可是那這問題就會來了
you're going to poke a mouse
你要去戳老鼠
how do you know
那你要怎麼知道
What position did you poke at?
你戳到什麼位置才是對的
We poke down every time
我們每次都是戳下去
See when the muscles shake
看什麼時候肌肉會發抖
we just want that right
我們就是要那是對
But you can't poke someone like this
可是你不可能這個樣子去戳人
right
對
So at that time there was a senior doctor of traditional Chinese medicine
所以那時候就有中醫師學長
just teach me how to feel the pulse
就教我如何去把脈
they will say why
他們就會說為什麼
I can't tell the difference
我就分不出來
Pregnant women's pulse will be slippery
孕婦的脈會滑滑的
But I'm going to take the boy's pulse
但是我去把男生的脈
Then
然後
Then there was one time in that
後來就是有一次在那個
The Department of Health has organized the Chinese Medicine Research Conference
衛生署他們有辦那個中醫藥研查會
I was
我那時候
I talked about this with teachers from other countries
我跟其他國家的老師講這件事情
I say it's very disturbing
我說這件事情非常令人困擾
I am really good at saving the world
我在真救世也滿好的技術
And foreign scholars like it very much
而且外國學者很喜歡
But is there any way
但是到底有沒有人有辦法
Do quantitative methods to help everyone
做定量的方法去幫助大家
Interpretation
判讀
Then until about 2014
後來一直大概到2014年的時候
American MIT
美國MIT
They are really scholars
他們就真的是有學者
They published a study called
他們就發表了一項研究叫做
action
動作
microscope
顯微鏡
is that it can be more than just
就是它可以不只是
the lips
嘴唇
or
或者是
pulse
脈搏
it can help you zoom in
它可以幫你放大
So you can clearly judge
所以就是你可以很清楚的去判定
is this a patient
這是不是一個病人
is it healthy or sick
它是健康的還是病人
or it lips what it's talking about
或是它唇語它在講什麼
Yes, and with this technology
對 然後有了這個技術之後
then actually
然後其實就
You can actually apply it to
你事實上是可以把它應用到
The pulse condition of traditional Chinese medicine is interpreted
中醫的脈象去判讀的
Right and so this is Chinese medicine
對 然後所以這是中醫
Why is it now the subject of Zhengjiu technology?
為什麼現在就是蒸久技術這一門
It is now de facto important in East Asia
它現在是東亞事實上很重要的
a door
一門
precious
寶
The reason people will call it a real treasure
人家會稱為它是真寶的原因
And it's actually recognized by the United Nations
而且事實上是聯合國也認可的
yes then so honestly
對 然後所以老實說
thank you very much for your speech today
非常感謝你今天的演講
thank you for this
就是這給他的謝謝
Thank you very much for your points
非常謝謝你的分
sorry
對不起
that thank you so much for sharing
那個非常謝謝你們分享
that is me
就是說我
Your sharing is actually
您的分享其實
in my feeling
在我的感覺上
A very important part is to say
一個非常重要的部分就是說
What Du Congming said at the time
杜聰明當時講的事情
from a certain point of view
某個角度來講
On the one hand, we can say that it actually has a vision
我們一方面可以說它其實有遠見
And conveniently, it can be said that this is still there today.
而方便也可以說這也是到今天還在
In justice, right?
正義之中 對不對
Now I kind of want to borrow
那我現在有點想藉著
Do a self-reflection on what you just said
您剛剛講的話來做一個自己的反省
That is to say, in fact, this is what we study
就是說其實這也是我們研究這個
History of Modern Traditional Medicine
現代傳統醫療史
a very special point
一個很特殊的一點
It's just that what we study is completely non-committal.
就是我們研究的事情滿無交難的
As of today, there is no general conclusion
到今天都還沒有概觀論定
contemporary relevance
都一方面有當代的相關性
Both sides are still in a high degree of justice
二方面都還在高度正義之中
such a situation
就是這樣子的一個情形
just say what i mean
就跟我意思說
like the one just now
比如像剛剛那個
Vice President Liu introduced
劉副院長介紹過
I'm in a department of history of science
我是在一個科學史的系裡
get a doctorate
得到博士學位
Then most of our friends have studied
那我們大部分的朋友大家研究的
That is to say, whether it is the history of physics or the history of biology
就是說無論是物理學史 生物學史
when historians began to study the meaning of coming
當歷史學家開始研究來的意思
That is to say, things have been concluded
就是說事情已經概觀論定了
truth we already know
真理我們已經知道了
That's called Ke Shuli
那已經起來叫科書理
So what historians do is start with
所以歷史學家做的事情都是從
we already know what the conclusion is
我們已經知道結論是什麼
At least write back the angle of who won
至少誰贏了的角度反寫回去
But only today I do this research
但唯獨今天我做這個研究
From a certain point of view until today
一直到今天某個角度來講
There is also a tall one
都還有很高的一個
means uncertainty and truth
就是說不確定性和真意
So I think on the one hand you feel
所以我想一方面你會感覺到
maybe a little resonant and inspiring
說不定有點共鳴和啟發性
But on the other hand we can also say
可另一方面我們也可以說
the truth of this matter
這件事情的真相
we don't quite know yet
我們還沒有完全知道
and even i kinda want to
而且甚至於我有點想
come further
進一步的來
say play the bad guy
就說扮演壞人
to say one thing
來講一個就是說
Actually from
其實從
Du Conghui
從杜聰明他
Who he doesn't accept when he mentions these studies
他提這些研究的時候不接受的人
Locke
譬如說在洛克
exist
在
Some of the Union Hospital
那個協和醫院的一些
medical scientist
醫科學家
They think it's easy to understand
他們覺得這是很容易了解的
because he felt
因為他覺得
You don't have any yin and yang elements
你沒有什麼陰陽五行
We also have 400 million say
我們也有四億說
We also have very long science
我們也有很長期的科學
We also have a lot of medicines that people say are useful
我們也有民間很多說有用的藥
But since the end of the 19th century
可是從19世紀末以來
We did a large clinical study results
我們做了大型臨床研究結果
proven medicine
證明了藥
Most of them are useless
絕大多數都是沒用的
that is
就是說
The American Medical Association was founded
美國的那個醫學會成立的
A great feature is to say
一個很大的功能就是說
It turned out that the previous medical period was useless
原來以前的醫療期都沒用
So according to what I just said
所以按照剛剛的講法
It is easy for them to regard Chinese medicine as
他們很容易把中醫看成
Same thing as their old medical
跟他們以前的醫療一樣的東西
So they also feel
那所以他們也覺得
we just did
我們才剛剛做
After such a glorious revolution in medicine
經歷過這樣一個光輝燦爛的醫學革命
Then know what medicine is useful
然後知道什麼是有用的藥
Then why should I waste my time on your side
那我何必在你這邊白白浪費時間
So what I mean is kind of saying
所以我的意思有點是說
I want to echo your argument
我想要呼應您的論點
is that this does have a high correlation
就是這的確有高度的相關性
But on the contrary, it also highlights that
但相反來講也凸顯出就是說
As far as Du Congming is concerned, he wants to propose such an idea
以杜聰明來講他想要提出這樣的想法
even put into practice
甚至付諸實現
it was difficult
本來就難困難的
so
所以
If you feel wronged sometimes, you should
您如果有時候有點委屈應該
Think Du Congming should
想想杜聰明應該
He even became the dean of National Taiwan University Hospital and couldn't give classes later
他連當台大醫院的院長後來都開不了課
I think all of us should be able to bear our grievances.
我想我們大家的委屈應該都可以忍得下來
That is to say, I kind of want to borrow this
就是說我是有點想借這個
to say is to say
來講就是說
In fact, one of the problems highlighted
其實凸顯出這個問題的一個
that is
就是說
a condition in progress
還在進行中的一個狀況
yes
是
Thank you Mr. Lei for your speech
謝謝蕾老師的演講
Today's class is a little bit
今天的課有一點
Make up for the previous time in medical school
彌補到以前在醫學院的時候
did not read part of the history of medicine
沒有念到醫學史的一部分
When it comes to Chinese medicine and Western medicine, I want to learn
談到中醫跟西醫的話我是要學習的
The first lesson we have to learn is that to bet is to bet
我們要學習的第一堂課就是要就是賭
It kind of echoes your saying that Su Dongpo is a medical student.
就有點呼應你在講蘇東坡就是學醫會人
So be careful when using drugs
所以在使用藥物的時候都很小心
In the research of Chinese and Western medicine, if we put the so-called positive attitude into research
中西醫的研究如果說我們把所謂正向立向去做研究的話
Perhaps in the part of western medicine, it emphasizes on getting rid of the bad effects first.
可能西醫的部分它比較強調的是先把不好的作用先去除掉
Don't treat people as experiments
不會把人當實驗品
But Chinese medicine is a kind of comparative experiment
但是中醫的話是一種比較實驗的
It's empirical science, it's been used for thousands of years and it really works
就是實證科學它已經用了幾千年確實有效
For example, this three-legged branch
像說這個三股科
Like acupuncture and moxibustion in terms of anesthesia and pain relief
像說針灸在麻醉跟止痛方面
it has indeed been demonstrated
它確實已經實證了
After the demonstration, the problem is that it will be a little controversial to study it with Western methods
實證以後問題是用西方的研究它這一部分會有一點爭議
The biggest controversy is that it comes from the placebo effect
最大的爭議是覺得是來自於安慰劑效應
In fact, many medicines do not necessarily have to be effective, but they are effective when we see a doctor.
其實很多藥其實是不一定要有效而是我們看到醫生就有效
Seeing a doctor is effective, so how to get rid of the placebo effect?
看到醫生就有效那怎麼樣去去除這個安慰劑的效應呢
In Western medicine, it is relatively clear that it proposes the Shuangman experiment
西方醫學它比較明確的它提出來就是雙滿實驗
Just like a doctor and a patient
就當醫生跟病人
The patient doesn't know what the drug is
病人都不知道藥物是什麼
Then when comparing the two
然後兩個去對照的時候
Then prove it
然後印證出來
It's true that this drug is more effective than a placebo
確實這個藥比安慰劑來得有效
that's called effective
那叫做有效
But what is really effective in medicine
但是醫療裡面真正的有效
In fact, placebos are also effective
其實安慰劑也是有效
So from a medical point of view
所以從醫學的角度來看
You can also skip to see
你也可以跳開來看說
Traditional Chinese Medicine and Western Medicine
中醫跟西醫
Whether it's a black cat or a white cat
不管是黑貓或白貓
It's a good cat to be able to catch him
能夠抓他屬就好貓
sick
自得了病
Why is the placebo effect not considered effective?
為什麼安慰劑效應就不能算是有效呢
This is what we do in medical school
這也是我們在醫學院裡面
I often discuss whether I sold some medicine
經常在探討到底有賣了一些藥
including food
包括食品
If the consumer finds it effective
如果消費者覺得他有效
why don't you sell him
你為什麼不賣給他
Selling the placebo effect is also a good effect
賣安慰劑效應也是一個很好的效應
So from a valid point of view
所以從有效的角度來看
That's what you said just now
也就是剛才你在講的說
When viewed from another point of view
從另一型的角度去看的時候
he will show up and say
他就會出現說
Nothing wrong with looking clinically effective
沒有錯看起來臨床是有效的
But after proof
但是實證以後
Maybe he's the same as the placebo
也許他跟安慰劑是一樣的
That's also in medicine
那這也是醫學裡面
Actually the subtle part
其實很微妙的那一部分
so this controversy
所以這個爭議
I don't think it's easy
我是覺得不太容易就是說
When we want to use the words of traditional Chinese medicine
當我們要把傳統醫學中醫的話
I'm talking about Sashi
談的是軍臣佐史
He mixes a lot of medicine
他很多藥術混在一起
So take out its components
所以要把他的組成分拿出來
In fact, as my partner just said,
其實像剛剛這位夥伴所講的說
In fact, there are some other metabolites
其實裡面還有一些其他的代謝物
Might work
說不定也有效
But you only analyze the same time every time
但是你每次只分析一樣的時候
It doesn't actually prove that
其實並不能證明說
His effect comes from this ingredient
他的效果是來自於這個成分
Ephedrine is a special case
麻黃素是一個特殊的案例
happens to have one main ingredient
剛好是有一個主要成分
Then find its components from traditional medicine
然後從傳統醫藥裡面找到他的組成分
This case is very rare
這個案例非常少
Because the entire treatment process of traditional Chinese medicine
因為整個中醫藥的處理歷程
it's not that simple
它就不是那麼單純
That's what I think our show today
這也就是我想我們今天這個節目
That is to say, in this topic
就是說這個題目裡面
I really admire Dr. Du Congwen
我倒是蠻敬佩杜聰文博士
he was at that time
他在那個年代
just what you said
就剛你講的說
he's on the edge
他在邊緣裡面
then go find one
然後去找到一個
Quite able to become a main axis of the protagonist
蠻能夠成為主角的一個主軸
It's an interesting piece of history from this point of view.
這個角度倒是蠻有趣的一段歷史
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, Dr. Lei, for your wonderful speech today.
謝謝蕾博士今天精彩演講
That's why I'm very interested in Dr. Du Congming's retrograde spellcasting
就是我對那個杜聰明博士這個倒行逆施法非常感興趣
Because I think his is similar to our current transfer medicine to a certain extent
因為我覺得他這個跟我們現在這個轉醫醫學是不是有一定程度的類似性
Because transfer medicine is to combine basic and clinical research
因為轉醫醫學就是想把基礎跟臨床的研究做一個結合
Of course, you can also start from the basics.
那當然也可以從基礎開始做
Then find it effective and then apply it to animals
然後發現有效之後再運用到動物
and then apply it to humans
然後再運用到人類的身上
But we sometimes issue some phenomena clinically
但我們有時候很多時候是從臨床上發行一些現象
Then go back and talk about designing some experiments
然後再回去看說去設計一些實驗
Let's see what the underlying mechanism is
去看說這個基礎的機制到底是什麼
Then you say that the matter of using people as experiments is not necessarily not on the CE level.
那你說就是拿人做實驗這件事情是Ce上面也未必是沒有
Like we sometimes use some off label use
像我們有時候會用一些off label use
That is to say, if A is effective for disease A at the beginning
就是說一開始A要是對A病有效
But we may accidentally find that it is also effective in B disease
可是我們可能意外發現又在B病也有效
Then go back and see what the mechanism is.
那最後再回去看說這個機制到底是什麼
So this is not necessarily an experiment with humans.
所以說這個也未必不是用人來做實驗
yes so i think this
對所以我覺得這個
In fact, I feel like what the gentleman said just now is to say
其實我覺得就像剛剛就是那個那個先生講的就是說
In fact, there may be many effective ingredients in traditional Chinese medicine.
其實中藥或許裡面有很多是有效的成分
It's just that we haven't used some so-called
只是我們還沒有用一些所謂的
It's just a scientific method recognized by the West to formalize
就是西方認可的科學的方法去正式而已
Thanks
謝謝
I will respond first
我先是回應一下
The gentleman you just mentioned means that
剛剛那個先生您提到就是說
poison problem
是毒的問題
In fact, what Mantre said is that
其實Mantre一講就是說
Changshan is poison
長山就是毒
just say yes now
就是現在就講說是有
And it is a poison in the compendium of this article
而且本條的綱目裡它是毒
also poisonous
也是毒
So actually from this point of view
那所以其實從這角度來講
there is a part that says
有一個部分就是說
accumulated knowledge
原來累積的知識
Some knowledge about toxicity
有部分就關於毒性的知識
And later, like the one I just used by Chen Guofu
而且後來像我剛剛陳果福他用的那個
When he used it, he used to call it Jiemao Pill
用的時候他本來用的叫解虐丸
He knows not to use it on pregnant women
他知道不要用在孕婦身上
And this means that
而且這樣解的意思就是說
Don't use it casually on others
你不要隨便亂用在人家身上
Because I know it's poisonous
因為知道有毒
You have to wait until someone's sadism is cured
你要等到人家虐疾好
It's happened to a certain extent
已經發作到某個程度了
In other words, you're more certain of his sadism.
換句話說你比較確定他的虐疾
But in fact he was
可是其實他那時候也是
The way to cure the doctor will not be to torture the worm, right?
解醫的方法也不會是虐緣蟲對不對
at least when you're sure
至少你比較肯定的時候
You are only halfway to cure this disease
你才半路去解這個病
in fact they
就是其實他們
What I mean by this is that
我這樣講的意思有一點是說
you are right
您講的是對的
on the one hand that is
一方面就是說
this is an important concern
這是個很重要的關懷
But in fact, they have accumulated some
然後可是其實他們以前也累積了一些
relevant knowledge
相關的知識
On the other hand, it is also the other way around.
那可另外一方面也反過來講就是說
directly like fruit skin
像成果膚那時候直接
when serving to others
拿給別人吃的時候
It's actually a bit dangerous.
其實是的確是有點危險的做法
In addition to what you just said
那另外您剛剛講的
Possible effect
Possible effect
This is indeed a question that many people will ask
這的確是非常多人會提到的一個問題
But this kind of echoes
可是這有點呼應到
the one in front
剛剛前面那位
That lady, what you just said is that
那位那個小姐您剛剛講的就是說
as far as i know
現在就我所知
That truth can indeed be applied to animals
那個真究的確可以用在動物身上
That is to say, it is already effective
就是說已經有效了
not employing
不是用人的
not use human blood
不是用人的血味
So this is actually a
那所以這其實是一個
just to say
就說明就是說
At least in animals
至少真究在動物身上
This must not be a possible effect
這一定不是Possible effect
It must be working for some other reason
一定是有別的原因才有效的
then
那然後
The last thing you said was that
您剛剛最後講的就是說
Actually Possible effect
其實Possible effect
also a good thing
也是一個很好的東西
why would
為什麼要
It means you do the two-chamber experiment
就是說你做雙房實驗
Just take it as if to exclude it from your evaluation
只是把它好像排除在你的評估之外
You just said this
您剛剛講的是這個
Actually this
其實這個
i know a case
我知道一個案例
that's because
就是因為
That is to say, at Harvard University
就是說在哈佛大學
Their Otentative Medicine Office
他們的Otentative Medicine Office
there is a researcher
有一位研究者
he is doing this research
他就在做這個研究
that is
就是說
Is it possible to think through this research
可不可以透過這個研究來想
How to strengthen placible effect
如何來強化placible effect
That said, don't think of it as just
就是說不要把它當成只是把
row measure out such a thing
排measure out這樣一個東西
Then this is a bit close to Du Congming's idea
那這有點像跟杜聰明的想法接近
It means we find something of value
就是說我們找到有價值的東西
to design new research methods
來設計新的研究法
Then try to understand its possible function
那來設法 來了解它可能的功能
probably this is the case
大概是這樣的情形
Thank you for the situation you just said
那謝謝您剛剛說的那個情形
I might have to ask you
我可能要跟您請教一下
I have heard it many times
我有聽過好多次
but i don't know very well
但我不是很了解
The details of that translation medicine
那個這個translation medicine的細節
so i'll ask you again
所以我再來跟您請教
Thanks
謝謝
I am after chemistry
我是學化學之後
I have always been interested in Chinese medicine
一直是上對中醫有點有興趣
but never had a chance to do it
但是一直沒有機會去做
I thought about doing some research to help
曾經考慮過要做一些幫忙研究
Then I switched to immunity
後來我轉到免疫力方面
Finally I learned fine medicine
最後我學了細醫
so in fact i am
所以事實上我是
The main character is you so I don't want to talk about myself
這主角是你 所以我不想多講我自己
No, then just a dermatologist
不是 後來只是皮膚科醫師
That is also to continue to have an extreme interest in Chinese medicine
那也是還是繼續對中醫有極度的興趣
but never had a chance to do
但是一直沒有機會做
One after another, the views on Chinese and English are not the same
陸續的話對中英的看法也不太一樣
Then the research is not the same
然後研究也不太一樣
So I'm thinking I've gained a lot today
所以我在想今天收穫很多
i was thinking
我在想說
in fact you may have said
事實上也許你也講了
this mystery this is
這個謎這個是
I'm talking about whether he was at that time
我在講是不是他那時候
Because he wrote the 60,000
因為他寫了那個六萬
very amazing
非常了不起的
he wrote sixty thousand
他寫了六萬
but he skimmed the words of the book
但他涉略了那個書本的話
Probably not necessarily 100 times, 100 times
大概不一定是100倍、100倍
he may have this amazing ability
他也許有這個驚人的能力
able to see
能夠去看
Then he read the history of the nations
然後他又又列國歷史
so he saw some evidence base
所以他看到一些evidence base
There was no Clean your trial
當初沒有Clean your trial
But finally I keep feeling
但是終於我一直覺得
There is no evidence base
就是沒有evidence base
not gone
就不是沒有了
it works
就是有效嘛
did not do trial
並沒有做trial
But looking at the words of thousands of years
但是看這麼幾千年來的話
Grandfather began to say
老祖宗開始說
In the end, in fact, there can be evidence
那最後事實上是可以有evidence出來
Are you looking at history?
是不是在看歷史上面
Articles written by Congming
都從明寫的文章
It can be seen that he saw some often an example
可以看得出來他看到一些常常是一個例子
Maybe there are other examples
也許有其他例子
So of course he speaks in English
所以當然他英文講的話
intrigue
intrigue
He thinks it works
他覺得是有效的
so he saw this
所以他看到這個
so he saw some evidence
所以他看到一些evidence
Then he said he was going to push
然後他說是要推
And said he believes that all Chinese medicines are effective
並說他相信所有中藥都有效
but it will work
但是一定有效的
So if you look at those with more evidence
所以是如果看那些比較有evidence的
for research
拿來做研究的話
It should work like this
應該會有效果這樣子
this is
這個是
eight door farmer
是八門農夫
so i thought this i wanted to find out
所以我想這個我想了解一下
Is there such a possibility in history?
在歷史上面是不是有這樣的可能性
maybe what you just said
也許是你剛剛講的
i just didn't hear fully
我只是沒有完全聽到
The second is the fact that traditional Chinese medicine needs to last until the end
第二就是事實上中藥需要到最後
in fact it should be
事實上是應該是
If it is a chemical drug
就是化學的藥物的話
It is what we made and traditional Chinese medicine
就是我們做出來的東西跟中藥
It is the identity in Chinese medicine
是中藥裡面的身份
all chemicals
都是化學物
chemicals are the same thing
化學物是一樣的東西
It's not like something made in a lab
並不是說是在實驗室做出來的東西
is a chemical
是一種化學物
inside the plant
在植物裡面
So it's another
所以就是另外一種
are likely to be the same
都有可能是一樣的
in fact it is
事實上也是
Like for example Tuxol these all become
像比如說Tuxol這些都變成是
Later, some medicines from western medicine practitioners
後來是西醫人一些藥
So in fact it should be the same
所以事實上是應該是沒有兩樣
The second is
第二就是
Now I feel more and more
現在也個人越來越覺得
suck a lot
吸很多當
Just relying on one medicine may not be enough
就是靠一種藥可能不夠
so it is always needed
所以是一直需要
Just use combination
就是要用combination
that so
那所以
So here's the word
所以這邊的話
In fact, Chinese medicine can be a kind of
事實上是中醫那邊可以是一種
the therapy
的therapy
or because i learned a word
或是因為我學到一個字
Another person is interested in Chinese medicine
另外一位對中醫有點興趣
he too
他也是
Too
也是
is that he is totally
就是他是完全是
evidence-based research scientist
evidence-based research的科學家
But he also intrigued
但是他也intrigued
He said this is complex formulation like this
他說這是complex formulation這樣子
So by the end of the two probably will be in
所以到最後兩個可能是會在
will be merge together
會是merge在一起
Then I just talked about evidence-based
那剛我講evidence-based
It was just mentioned by the director
也是剛剛這位理事提到
is in fact
就是事實上是
That is to say
也就是剛才講說
In fact it is
事實上是
It is not said to be a real clinical trial
並沒有說是真正的clinical trial
But for thousands of years
但是幾千年來的話
It's a trial
是trial了
so many years
那麼多年了
Xi Yiduo hasn't done it yet
習一多還沒有做過
FDA approval can be obtained in about a few years
大概幾年就可以fda approval
But this has been done for thousands of years
但這個是做了幾千年
get some effective
得到某一些有效
not all will work
並不是所有都會有效
So my previous build looks like this
所以我的前建是這樣子
maybe repeat what you said
也許重複你是講的
But I think when people live
但是我想人們住在的時候
Learn my thoughts from you a little bit
稍微跟你學一下我的想法
It feels really late today
今天真是有相見很晚的感覺
So let's try and talk more later
所以我們以後多試一下多談一下
Or we can set up a club to discuss this matter
或是我們可以搞個club來談這件事情
I'm sorry, of course I'd rather
不好意思 當然我寧
ask the professor
請教教授
Just now we talked about Chinese medicine and Western medicine
剛我們談到中醫跟西醫
In our impression, that is to say, most people
在我們就是說大部分人的印象裡面
modern scientific treatment
現代的科學治療
Western medicine speed treatment is relatively fast
西醫速度治療是比較快速的
Chinese medicine treatment appears to be more
中醫治療就顯得比較
slower version slower better
比較慢版 比較慢慢的好
What kind of concept
請問這樣子的概念
Is this thinking correct?
這樣想法是不是正確的
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, let me respond first
謝謝 我先回應一下
The question raised by Liu Feiyang just now
剛剛那個劉飛揚提的問題
you just mentioned that
您剛剛提過就是說
that is to say ducong
就是說嘟叢
That is to say actually
就是說 其實
Yes, I think Du is smart
對 我覺得杜聰明
Du Congming is actually on this matter
杜聰明其實在這件事上
he has a very scientific stance
他有一個非常科學的立場
which means there is no doubt that we can feel
就是說毫無疑問的我們可以感覺到
He feels the value of traditional Chinese medicine or traditional Chinese medicine
他覺得傳統醫療文漢醫或中醫的價值
There's actually more to it than we know now
其實比我們現在知道的來得多
So he wants to develop a new research method
所以他要發展新的研究法
But how much he wasn't sure
可是究竟多少他並沒有確定
So he says there are three possible futures
所以他說有三個可能的未來
he was the first to say
他第一個就是說
If you find a lot of value
如果發現非常多都有價值
we really did
我們真的就這樣做了
That is to say, there is no Effidence
就是說沒有Effidence
We really do find a lot of value
我們真的去做發現非常多有價值
He said we should put it in medical school
他說我們應該把它放在醫學院
let students take electives
讓學生去選修
It is the situation of the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine we just talked about
就是我們剛剛講中醫院的狀況
The second is to say
第二個就是說
We found that only a few were valuable
我們發現只有少部分有價值
In fact, most of them are worthless
其實大部分都沒有價值
Then a small part should be incorporated into western medicine.
那就少部分要納入西藥就可以了
The third is that you find not only worthless
第三個就是說你發現不僅沒有價值
many worthless
很多都沒有價值
And it's toxic
而且反而又有毒性
He said you should quickly announce it to the public
他說你趕快跟社會大眾公佈
Tell everyone not to use
叫大家都不要用
He said that because everyone is busy using
他說因為大家都忙碌在用
It's not good now
現在也是不好
So he actually has a pretty open stance.
所以他其實是有一個蠻開放性的立場
Now open to outside positions
現在開放性的立場之外
you can really feel it
你的確可以感覺到說
He thinks it's definitely worth more than we know now
他覺得這個價值絕對比我們現在知道的來得多
And now I know from Changshan's standpoint
而且現在從長山立場就知道
he does know
他的確知道
Then he talked about massage, snake medicine, etc.
然後另外他講的推拿 講蛇藥等等
So he should have some personal energy
所以他應該是有一些親身的精力
That is to say, the value is relatively high.
就是說覺得這個價值來得比較高
Then this is connected to what you just said
那這邊就連接到您剛剛說的一點
In fact, most of us now feel that
其實我們現在大部分都會覺得說
Chinese medicine seems to be a chronic disease, right?
中藥好像是慢性病對不對
It can be seen that Du Congming's move is infectious disease
可以看杜聰明舉的就是傳染病
It means the saddle
就是指的是虐脊
So in fact, at that time
所以其實那個時代的時候
You think that when there is no Western medicine, Chinese medicine must be an acute disease
你想在沒有西醫的時候中醫得是急性病
Therefore, it is much slower than what we now teach Chinese medicine.
所以說有慢多我們現在對中醫的講法
Some are actually relative to this history after
有一些其實是相對於這個歷史之後
Because you have to compare with the pressure given to you by Western medicine
因為你要相對於西醫的給你的壓力
You have to maintain an idea that you have created
你要自我維護創造出來的一個想法
It's not exactly the original historical situation
就不完全是原來歷史完全的狀況
that's probably the case
那大概是這樣的情形
In addition, Chairman Liu Feihong, what you just mentioned is that
然後另外劉飛鴻議長您剛剛提的就是說
In fact, it could be a problem of drug mixing.
就其實可以是藥的混合的問題
Christian Zongming specifically mentioned that
基督宗明有特別這樣提
not only did he say
就他不僅說
we can do it in reverse
我們可以反過來做
experimental therapeutics
用實驗治療學
Then do it first on people
然後先在人上做
And he said that unit medicine is not necessary
而且他說不一定要單位藥
he said he would
他就說他就
He even gave many examples saying
他甚至還給了很多例子說
why he imagined
他想像中為什麼
The effect of the medicine after several medicines get together
等到幾位藥聚在一起之後的藥效
Possibility of altered potency
藥效改變了的可能性
So in this sense
所以這個意義上來講
He did mention it early
他的確是很早就在提
what we think today
我們今天想的這種
It is not necessary to pursue the goal of unit drug
不一定要追求單位藥的目標
Then this point at the time
然後這一點在當時
Japan has begun to change
日本已經開始變論了
that's probably sober
那大概是這樣的清醒
right
對
ask the professor
請教一下教授
Just now we said that poison
剛剛我們說那個藥毒
That's what many of our concepts mean
那可是我們很多概念裡面就是說
Many diseases sometimes require
很多病有的時候都是需要
Fighting poison with poison isn't it?
以毒攻毒不是嗎
that is to say
那還有就是說
we have many cypresses
我們很多谷柱柏
Unified thoughts
大家統一的想法
Many people think that traditional Chinese medicine is more
很多都認為說中藥比較
Suitable for conditioning this vitality
適合用來調理這個元氣方面
It is faster to use C1 to treat diseases
那治療病的話用C1比較快速
Is this the right idea, thanks
這樣是不是正確的理念 謝謝
In fact, I think what you just said is very complicated and interesting.
其實您剛剛講的事情我覺得就很複雜也很有趣
The first one is that your first sentence is actually
第一個就是您第一句話其實就是
Hu Ying, what the gentleman said just now is that if it is poisonous, right?
胡瑩剛剛那位先生講的就是說要就是毒嘛 對不對
So from a certain point of view it must be
所以某個角度來講一定是
Must be toxic, use with care
一定就是有毒性要小心使用
Then I remembered another thing you said, that is,
然後另外您講的一件事我就想起就是說
In my research I have asked for advice that is
在我做研究中我有請教就是說
Now to the Dean Zhang Henghong of Taichung Chinese Medical College
現在到台中中國醫藥學院的張恆宏院長
At that time, he was the director of Changgen's Institute of Traditional Medicine
我那時候他是在長根的傳統醫學研究所當所長
He is promoting the notification system of adverse reactions of traditional Chinese medicine
他在推動中醫藥的不良反應的通報系統
He said Taiwanese are
他說台灣人就是
is the most messy eater
就是最會亂吃
Because just saying it all has no side effects
因為就把所有的都說這沒有副作用的
eat as food
當作食物來吃
But in fact, if he was used as medicine before, it must be effective
可是其實如果他以前被當藥用一定是有藥效
So in fact maybe I because I don't have one
所以事實上可能我因為我沒有一個
Notification system for adverse drug reactions
藥物不良反應的通報系統
so you don't know what bad effects it has
所以你不知道它有什麼不良的效果
So this is actually a
那所以其實這也是一個
I just said
我剛剛講就是說
If you originally came to see the food therapy tradition of Chinese medicine
你如果本來看中醫的食療傳統
Many are real
本來就很多是實境
I think this food can be used as medicine
覺得這個食物可以當藥物
So some things you can't be careful about
所以有些東西你不能夠要很小心
But now we feel like saying
但是我們現在就會覺得說
Chinese medicine is consistent with chronic
中醫都一致慢性
all itchy
都一條癢
Then did not eat fitness
然後沒吃健身
It's okay to eat
吃了也沒有問題
That is to say, it is actually somewhat
就是說這其實有些
It wouldn't be what people thought a hundred years ago
不會是一百年前的人的想法
So the other way around
那所以反過來講
For example, like the Dean Zhang Wenhong I just mentioned
就是比如像我剛剛講的張文宏院長
The adverse reaction system of traditional Chinese medicine that he wants to promote
他想推動的那個中藥的不良反應系統
In fact, it is also equivalent to one of the modernization of traditional Chinese medicine.
其實也是等於像中藥現代化的一個
important step
重要的一個步驟
probably like this
大概是這樣子的情形
Dr Ray I'm sorry please
雷博士對不起請
i want to ask
我想問一下
I just mentioned that young boy from that continent
剛剛有提到那個大陸那個土幼幼的
What part of the study is decantin
研究什麼清潢素的那個部分
it is this part of the research conduct program
它是這個研究行為程序的這個部分
marry us or something
是跟我們婚姻還是什麼
can you add
可不可以補充
let me compare to this
讓我比較對這個
where is he
他的什麼地方
With our present set is
跟我們現在這一套是
relatively similar or
比較相似或者說
he is part of some inspiration
他是有一些啟發的部分
isn't it
不是嗎
right
對
because we didn't mention
因為我們不是有提到
said he actually had
說他其實有
it's me right
就是我對
because i'm a layman
因為我是外行
i don't know
我不太知道
that is to say he
就是說他
Is there a certain part of the program
是不是有某一部分的程序
There is also a breakthrough
也是有一個突破
and come in from a different point of view
然後從個不同的觀點進來
i don't know much
我不太了解
This time Nobel talks about his
這次的諾貝爾講他的
talk to one of our local
跟我們這個地方的一個
may need to be supplemented
可能需要補充
let me know something
讓我清楚知道一些
Thank you
謝謝你
Thanks
謝謝
Well actually you asked a very good question
好 其實您問的是一個非常好的問題
And it's a question I really want to know
而且是我自己非常想知道的問題
that's what i think you're feeling
就是我想您引然的感覺是說
The story of the long mountain I just told
我剛剛講的前面這個長山的故事
There's a lot of element of surprise, right?
有很多令人意外的元素 對不對
Very different from 12345
跟12345很不一樣
But the story of Qinghaosu
但是清豪宿的故事
Right now the act of righteousness is here
現在的真義行就在這裡
Because when Nobel speaks
因為諾貝爾講的時候
He is not awarded to Chinese medicine, right?
他不是頒給中醫 對不對
He is awarded for the study of a modern science
他是頒給一個現代科學的研究
as if to say
就彷彿是說
can happen anywhere
在任何地方都可能發生
Research that any scientist can come and do
任何科學家都可以來進行的研究
And there are plenty of critics who will say
而且有很多批評者會說
This is actually the CCP’s
這其實就是中共為了當時
The needs of the Vietnam War
越戰的需要
Invest a lot of resources in the country for auditions, right?
投入國家大量資源進行海選 對不對
Then found a lot of drugs to conduct research
然後找了非常多藥物來進行的研究
This is completely a typical process of new drug development
這完全是新藥研發的典型的過程
Nothing to do with Chinese medicine
跟中醫完全無關
So this is not Chinese medicine
所以這不是中藥
you just kinda wanted to ask me this
您剛剛有點想要問我這一件事
so i'm going to be frank
所以我要坦白的說
That is to say, because Tuyou TV is actually involved in the controversy over Shenwei's award
就是說因為圖幼電視其實涉及到神衛得獎的爭議
So the information we have seen so far is not complete.
所以目前為止我們看到的資料還不完整
But I can at least know a few things
但我至少可以知道幾件事
first thing to say
第一件事就是說
We just told this story
我們剛剛這個故事來講
when this is not a political decision
當這個不是一個政治的決定
Then I said it like this
然後是我這樣講好了
Now, for example, after Tuyoushi happened
現在譬如說圖幼視發生之後
If we look at the New York Times report
我們如果看紐約時報的報導
would say that this is a typical scientific study
就會講說這是一個典型的科學研究
nothing weird, right?
沒有什麼很奇怪的地方對不對
If we take the story of Changshan just now as an example
那如果以剛剛長山的故事來講
That doesn't sound like a typical science study
那聽起來不是一個典型的科研究
Instead, it involves breakthroughs in some scientific research methods
反而是涉及到一些科研究方式的突破
only results
才能有的結果
You ask me this question again, right?
您再問我這個問題對不對
So now we put this story back into this history
那所以現在我們把這個故事放回到這段歷史裡的話
prompt people to start looking for
促使人們開始找
Looking for anti-abuse drugs in China and Australia
在中澳裡面找抗虐藥的
In fact, it is related to the atypical story of Changshan
其實就跟長山這個非典型的故事有關
Then according to a
然後根據一部來講
Now why on earth would you find
現在究竟為什麼會找到
Ching Pao Su's story
清拋素的故事中
I recently read one that just came out
我最近有讀到一個就是剛出版
That is, a verbal interview for this 523 plan
就是說對於這個523計畫進行一個口頭訪問
Someone made a visit of hundreds of pages
就有個人做了一個幾百頁的訪問
Then I read it and felt like saying
然後我讀完的感覺是說
And I think that's what the author intended
而且我覺得那是作者的原意
That is to say, the credit is not
就是說其實這個功勞不是
It shouldn't be Tu Youyou
不應該是徒佑佑讀想
Because to a large extent another scholar
因為很大程度上是另外有一位學者
He quickly put this screened list
他很快的把這個篩選的名單
reduced to a dozen miles
縮減到十幾個里
Then it already contained the cleaning paraffin at that time
然後那裡面已經包含了當時的清拋素
And the scholar himself
而且那位學者他本身
Doing this screening can effectively
做這個篩檢能夠有效的把
In the process of narrowing down the objects of screening
篩檢的對象縮減的過程中
A large part of him has been using Changshan since then.
很大一部分他就是以來用到長山
as a reference point
作為一個參考點
in his opinion
就他認為說
Because traditional Chinese medicine obviously
因為以前中醫顯然
Already found an effective drug against sadism
已經曾經找到過有效制虐疾的藥
so it's hard for him to imagine saying
所以他很難想像說
without
沒
later
後來搞不好
Maybe there will be later
搞不好後來還有
So he took the recipe with Changshan in it and took it away
所以他把方子裡面有長山的他把他拿走
Because of this, because those prescriptions are likely to mean
因為這樣因為就說那些那些方子很可能就表示
is proven effective because of Chang Shan
是因為長山而證明有效的
Then it is looking for the common ground in the middle
然後它裡面在找中間的共同點
and help it focus to
然後幫助它focus到
That is to say, the study of Qinghaosu
就是說清豪宿這個研究
So my answer to your question just now is to say
所以我對您剛剛的問題的回答就是說
My answer to you just now is to say
我對您剛剛的回答是說
1. I don’t have a story similar to Changshan to tell Haosu
一 我沒有一個類似長山的故事可以講清豪宿
Because there's a lot of historical material for that story
因為那個故事的史料有非常多
I have never seen
我都沒有看到過
But I based on oral interviews done by others
但我根據現在別人做的口訪的
A very detailed oral interview
一個很細緻的口訪的話
i think this thing
我覺得這個事情
At least part of it is
至少有一個部分就是說
At that time, Tuluo could quickly narrow down the screening
當時塗誘誘能夠迅速的縮小篩檢的
When screening Chinese medicine items
篩檢的中藥的項目的時候
In fact, it is used
其實是有運用到
That is to say, related to related matters
就是說跟有關的有關的事情
But I can't explain the details more clearly.
可是細節我還沒辦法講得更清楚
so
所以
So in the story just now, I can only say that there is no way
所以剛剛的故事中我只能說到這裡沒辦法
Said that this is a story completely parallel to Changshan
說這是一個跟長山完全平行的故事
Teacher, I am very grateful for your speech today
老師我很謝謝你今天的演講
And so the story about Tu Youyou's Nobel Prize
然後所以關於土優優的諾貝爾獎的故事
Then I want to add this paragraph
然後我想補充一下這一段
In fact, the Nobel Prize was awarded to Tu Youyou at the same time
事實上諾貝爾獎在頒獎給土優優的同時
Their works that won the Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine that year
他們那一年的諾貝爾生理醫學獎的作品
Also included was awarded to Mork for his original invention
還有包括有頒給莫克當初發明
It's the medicine for blindness in Africa.
就是給非洲治合盲症的那個藥
Right, and so the Nobel Prize committee judges
對 然後所以諾貝爾獎他們的委員會評審
They themselves said they didn't award those two drugs
他們自己有說他們並不是頒給那兩個藥物
they awarded
他們頒給
In fact, what they're awarding is the method that actually discovered the drug in the first place.
事實上他們在頒給的是當初真正發現這個藥物的方法
Then 10 years ago, the academicians of the Chinese Academy of Sciences opposed
然後就是10年前中研院院士們反對
it's important
要很重要這件事
But in fact, they should not have the academicians of Academia Sinica to remember
可是事實上他們應該沒有中研院院士還記得
During the Cultural Revolution
在文革的時期
Then those were sent out of the mainland
然後那些被送出大陸
Then to those chemists in America
然後到美國的那些化學家
In fact, many of them were taken in by Mokda Pharmaceuticals' laboratory in New York.
其實有很多是被莫克達藥廠在紐約的實驗室收容的
Yes, and in fact, Mokda and the others are very interested in Chinese medicine.
對 然後事實上莫克達他們對中醫藥這一塊很有興趣
Then they also silently protect this piece
然後他們也默默的保護這一塊
yes then so
對 然後 所以
Then the award to Tuyouyou should be in 2011
然後頒獎給圖遊友應該是2011年的時候
Then other recapitalization at that time
然後那時候別的改資
Because he is actually very interested in making medicine
因為他其實對做藥很有興趣
Yes and he is also right
對 然後他也對
He is interested in making vaccines and then public health
他對做疫苗然後公衛方面
He is very interested in making medicine
他做藥都很有興趣
And then they already said
然後那時候他們就已經講過
In fact, it should be awarded to China
其實應該要頒給中國
It's the Chinese medicine
就是中藥這一塊
Yes, then who will it be awarded to?
對 然後要頒給誰
At that time, I actually thought of Tuyouyou at first.
那時候其實一開始想到就是圖遊友
But it's not because he invented
可是其實並不是因為他發明
one word sadism drug
一個字虐疾的藥
because what they really want to praise is
因為他們真正想要表揚的是
The quick help in traditional Chinese medicine
中藥裡面那些快速的幫助
how do you tell the difference
你如何去區分
how are we going to stuff it
我們要怎麼樣塞藥的
Those who have been tired by the Lord for thousands of years
就是那些千年來主先累
The Chinese advocate the wisdom of getting tired first
中國人主先累接下來的智慧
What they're actually giving awards for is that set of things
他們事實上在頒獎要表揚的是那一套東西
Yeah, and because there's a lot of politics involved
對 然後因為這中間牽涉到很多政治因素
you can't tell the truth
你不能光明真大說
We want to praise those who because Wenger
我們要表揚那些因為溫格
those assets that were then sent to the United States
然後被送到美國的那些資產
Yes, so I can only tell everyone
對 然後所以就只能告訴大家說
what we want to commend is
我們想要表揚的是
can help you quickly find
能夠幫助大家快速找到
Approaches to new drug development
新藥開發的方法
this set
這一套
That's Nobel's Lecture
那是諾貝爾的講迴園
They said it themselves
他們自己有講出來這一段
I haven't heard
我沒有聽過
and such words
而且這樣的話
This story is the opposite of what we usually hear
這故事跟我們一般聽到的是相反的
right
對不對
these actually exist
這些事實上是存在的
And there are people who will remember this passage
而且就是是還有人會記得這一段
Because who protected those chemists in the first place?
因為當初是誰保護那些化學家們
top decision-makers
那些做決策的高層
In fact, there are still people from this world
其實是還有從活台這世界上的
right then
對 然後
So these stories are
所以這些故事是
someone is willing to admit
要有人願意承認
Then they can
然後他們才能夠
was recorded
被記載下來
then in fact
然後事實上
Nobel talks about how they award
諾貝爾講他們頒獎的
Meaning they want to speed up
意思就是他們希望能夠加快
New steps to be developed
新要開發的腳步
because now everyone says
因為現在大家都說
new development
新要開發
The process is too long
流程脫太長了
Then it's because the process is too long
然後就是因為流程脫太長
So the price of new drugs will become very expensive
所以新藥的藥價就會變得非常的昂貴
then you get expensive
然後你變得很昂貴
No matter how good the medicine you make
就算你做出來的藥再好
And then the problem is that it becomes a new drug
然後可是問題是就會變成新藥
we can't afford it
大家都負擔不起
every country says so
每一個國家都這麼說
Right, and so in fact what they want to change is
對 然後所以事實上他們想要改變的是
This whole thing is almost on the verge of collapse.
這一整個幾乎已經趨近於崩壞的
health care and medicine system
健保和醫藥制度
thanks i'm very interested
謝謝 我很有興趣
I hope you will provide me with that information later
希望您待會把那個資料提供給我
Because I don't know what you just said
因為你剛剛講的我都不知道
Then my impression is quite different
然後跟我的印象蠻不同的
so i'm curious to know more
所以我很好奇想更知道一些
Thanks
謝謝
Teacher, if I have found the information
老師那如果我有找到資料的話
i can send you a letter
我可以寄信給你們
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
teacher this gentleman
老師 這一位先生
Teacher, thank you for this talk
老師謝謝你的這個talk
In fact, your article is about Teacher Du Congming
其實你這篇就是有關杜聰明老師的這篇文章
I got it by accident
其實是我偶然而得的
Then I just want to ask a question, that is
那我就是想問一個問題就是說
There is an appreciation for Chinese medicine formed by Dr. Du Congming
有關於杜聰明博士形成一個讚賞中醫藥
Then continue the research on medicines and medicines
然後持續對於和藥的這樣一個研究的
the idea
這個想法
Are you sure about the idea? Are there any related materials now?
想法的確信有沒有現在有沒有一些相關的使料
Explain that in fact, his thinking has actually changed.
說明說其實他這個想法其實是有所改變
For example, he might be like Mr. Fussian from before
比方說他可能從之前的像富斯年先生
Or a person like Mr. Sun Zhongan who upholds this careless position
或是像孫中安先生那樣一個秉持這個稀意的立場
It’s just that he was like what Mr. Li you just said, he may have some experience in life
只是他後來就像李老師你剛剛說的他可能生活上的一些經驗
or some of his scientific intuition or something
或者是他的一些科學上的直覺或怎麼樣
Or it is such a belief in Chinese medicine in this battlefield formed by his Open Minded
或者是說他Open Minded的所形成的這個戰場中醫藥的這樣一個確信
Is there a set of relevant materials that can be searched for again?
是不是有一些就是相關的使料可以去再去追尋的這一套
How did he form a process of talking about traditional Chinese medicine on the battlefield
他如何形成一個說戰場中醫藥的過程
Actually, I think this is Mr. Li, your speech today is very interesting.
那其實我覺得這個就是李老師你今天這個演講很有趣的
In fact, I think that in daily life, everyone will face
其實我覺得在日常生活當中每一個人都會面對
Especially including yourself or relatives or friends
特別是包含自己或者是親人或朋友
When they face this kind of B-Pool of disease
當他們面對疾病的這種這種B-Pool的時候
will still face this so-called dispute between Chinese and Western medicine.
都還是會面臨到這種所謂中西醫的之爭
Including the treatment of the recent colorectal cancer of Mr. Su Geliang
包括最近的那個蘇格亮先生的那個大腸癌的那個治療
In fact, we can also clearly see that one is a pancake.
其實我們也可以很清楚的看得到說一個是餅子
I don't want to go to Western medicine again
不願意去重上西醫
Another position is that
另外一個立場就是說
probably in the modernized this
可能在現代化的這個
Under this generality of modernity
現代性的這個大體之下
I just insist on western medicine and I don't accept it
我就是堅持西醫而我也不去接受
Such an award for variety shows
綜藝的這樣一個勳討
so i was thinking
所以我就在想說
In fact, as far as I am concerned
其實就我自己來講
when myself
當我自己
Make this medical decision for yourself
為自己做這個醫療決定
or for example parents
或是為譬如父母親
make such medical decisions
做這樣醫療決定
I still feel like saying
我還是會覺得說
I should still be
我還是應該是
Looking for this western doctor
尋著這個西醫的
Such a normal pipeline
這樣一個正常的管道
For example, in the context of this treatment
比如說在這個治療的脈絡下
Follow the path of Western medicine
走西醫的這個路子
Because at least for Chinese medicine
因為至少對於中醫來講
i may not understand
我可能不了解
Or just don't have that much
或是就是並不具備的這麼多
say maybe for some kind of cancer
說可能對於某樣的癌症
or gastroenteritis or something
或是什麼腸胃炎等等的
such an unusual disease
這樣一個尋常的這些疾病
Then does Chinese medicine have to have curative effect?
然後他是不是中醫要具有療效
Actually I don't
其實我並不會
If and when I have the right to make this decision
如果當我有這個決定的權利的時候
I would actually be like
我其實是會像
Mr. Fu Silin or Mr. Lu Xun said the same
傅思林先生或魯迅先生一樣說
I won't make that decision
我不會去做那個這個決定
But in the daily health care or food
可是在日常那些保健或是食物
Maybe we will often drink bitter tea
可能我們會常常喝苦茶
or herbal tea
或清草茶
but those are
可是那些都是
The Doubtful Orders of Traditional Chinese Medicine
漢醫藥的那些疑序
I feel like I can do it again
我又會覺得我是可以去做的
such an absorption
這樣一個吸收
So actually answer one
所以其實還是回答一個
it's fun
就很有趣
This dispute between China and the West
這個中西之爭
like before i thought
像之前我就想到
It seems that it is also in life
好像大概也是生活上
inspired by something
一些事情的啟發
just remind me of that
就讓我想到那個
Academician Tian Changning talked about
田長寧院士所談到
He said that he felt micro-learning was going to extremes
他說覺得微學要走極端
Is the research to do extreme
就是研究要做極端
Pursue excellence
追求卓越
It seems to be moderate on Weiren
在微人上面好像就要做中庸
But for us now
可是對我們現在來講
From the point of view of the present
從現在性來講
It seems to be a straight line development
好像就是一個直線發展
That is to say, everything about me is actually
就是說我凡事其實
just go to the extreme
就是要走到極端
to pursue excellence
要追求卓越
But in another category
可是在另外一個事物的範疇
For example, between people
比如說人與人之間
that treat each other
那個相待
it seems to go again
它好像又要走
what we call oriental wisdom
我們所謂的東方智慧
treat each other
這個相待
Then in these two cultures
那在這兩種這個文化當中
In fact, when I was faced with a
其實當我面對的是一個
I'm going to make this sick
我要使得這個病
able to be cured
能夠被治癒
or make this
或使得這個
I can push this thing further
我這個事物能夠進一步的推展
or people care about me
或是人與我關心
when you can get along
能夠融洽的時候
In fact, what we focus on
其實我們關注的事情
is the same thing
是同一個東西
just say in the method
只是說在方法上
or conceptually
或在觀念上
is there a difference
是有不同的區別
But in fact
但這中間其實
I'm fighting a judgment now
我現在是作戰一個判斷
I don't know what Mr. Lei thinks about this
我不曉得雷老師對這
Do you have any opinion on this?
這方面有沒有怎樣的看法
thanks for these two questions
謝謝就這兩個問題
The first question is to say
第一個問題就是說
We currently have very limited data
我們現在有的資料還是很有限
That means I can't rebuild
就是說我沒辦法重建
That is why it has such an idea
就是說它為什麼有這樣的想法
But it should be the period of early rule with Taiwan
可是應該是跟台灣早日治時期
The history of Chinese medicine in Taiwan at the beginning has a lot to do with it
剛開始的台灣中醫史有很大的關係
that is to say actually
就是說其實
At that time, those Chinese medicine practitioners were the first to come into contact with
當時那些中醫反而是最早接觸到
That is to say, people trained in modern science
就是說現代科學訓練的人
But we rarely talk about this part now
但這個部分我們現在很少講
Most of our history of medicine during the Japanese period is about
我們大部分講日時期的醫學史都是講
The history of Western medicine rarely talks about the history of Chinese medicine
西醫史很少講中醫史
So this part is still very under under study
所以這部分還非常under under study
but i feel that
但我覺得那個
You can feel strongly from Du Congming's story
你從杜聰明的故事中你會強烈的感覺到
He he he got inspiration with him over there
他他跟他在那邊得到的啟發
Then his discourse
然後他的論述的話
Because later it can't be realized
因為後來就沒辦法實現
So there's really no way to trace his development.
所以就其實沒辦法繼續追溯他的發展
Then we can read him another
那我們可以去讀他另外
I just talked about the class he gave after he went to the freshman year of high school
我剛剛講他去高一之後他開的課
historical materials left behind
留下來的史料
but I
但我
But I, I, I also doubt
可是我我我我也懷疑說
Still can't fully answer your question
還是沒辦法完全解答您的問題
Then your next question is to say
然後您後面那個問題就說
To supplement the one just now about
補充剛剛那個有關於就是
The significance of Ms. Tuyouyou's award in 15 years
15年土幼幼女士那個獲獎的意義
In fact, I should actually say that I was
其實我其實應該是說我當時
I'm going to test that Yangming business
我考那個陽明生意
The name is Luochunshan, and then I went to study physiology
名落春山後來我去念了生理
So basically I'm in the background of Physiology
所以基本上我是生理的背景
rather than the background of the catechism
而不是要理的背景
But that award-winning story of the young lady
可是那土幼幼女士的那個得獎的故事
just let me at least from the media
就讓我就至少從媒體上
It can be seen from relevant information
就是有關相關的資料看出來
first sure
第一確確
The Nobel is to be awarded to that party
Nobel是要頒給那個方
It is the method of extracting Qinghao tree
就是萃取出清豪樹的那個方法
The reason for that method
那個方法的原由
According to Ms.
根據土女士的表示
It is the one from the Northern and Southern Dynasties
它是來自於南北朝的那個
Ge Hong's book about clothes
葛鴻的一本衣書裡面所談到的
Then he compared him with this modern
然後他把他和現代的這個
scientific knowledge connects it
科學知識把它連起來
That's why the Qinghao tree was able to come out
所以清豪樹才能夠問世
I think this is a supplement
我覺得這個是補充
as if to say
就好像說
But for Ms. Tuyouyou's winner
但對土幼幼女士的得獎致使來講
he will feel that yes
他會覺得說是
Nobel
Nobel
The Nobel Prize is to honor this China and North Korea
Nobel Prize是 honor 這個中朝
But for the Nobel Committee
但是對於Nobel Committee來講
it's not actually
它其實並不是
It actually shows that, as the New York Times puts it,
它其實彰顯就是像紐約時報所講的
is that it is actually an ordinary scientific study
就是它其實是一個尋常的科學研究
found a new drug
找到了一個新藥
in an innovative way
用一個創新的方法
Found a drug that is extremely effective against abusers
找到了一個對虐極極為有效的藥物
So these two seem
所以就是這兩種好像
Maybe it's right for Tu Nv
可能對土女是對於
As far as native girls are concerned
就土女是來講
Its interpretation of the study goes like this
它對於這個研究的詮釋是這樣子
Westerners have different ideas from Westerners
那西方人有西方人不同的想法
Just to make such a supplement
就是作這樣一個補充
so you said
所以您講的
yes, that's what i think
對,這也是我印象中
the rights of others
就是說別人的權利
Then you just said
然後你剛剛講就是說
It learned from Ge Hong
它從葛紅那邊學到的
That is to say, one foot has limbs
就是說一腳就有肢
So I thought of low temperature extraction
所以後來想到低溫萃取
that this is indeed relevant
那這個的確是有關的
but if so
可是如果這樣的話
This connection is also weak, isn't it?
這連接也很弱對不對
That is to say, it is probably like this
就是說大概是這樣子的情形
But I'm going the other way
可是我有點反過來講
The one behind you just spoke longer
您剛剛後面那個講的比較長
Then there is the question of
然後就是說的問題
I turned it into another related question
我把它轉成另外一個相關的問題
that is
就是說
you see my story
你看到我的故事
My stories are all about success
我的故事講的都是成功的個案
right
對不對
Then others can say the other way around
那別人可以反過來說
Then you know that Du Congming will drive a few more
那你知道杜聰明另外來開幾個
Will our research be successful right away?
我們是不是馬上研究都會成功
I don't think Du Congming will be so sure
我想杜聰明也不見得會這樣的把握
So there are critics who say
所以會有批評者說
For example, the young lady just mentioned that someone went to Merc, right?
譬如說剛剛那個小姐姐提到有人去merc對不對
In fact, the one I just talked about in Xiehe Hospital
其實在協和醫院我剛剛講的那個
Then they made ephedrine
後來他們做出了麻黃素
Ephedrine can cure asthma
麻黃素可以去氣喘那個藥
And that was the general period of the Republic of China
而且那是一般的民國時期
Research considered a true breakthrough
被認為真正突破的研究
He was later poached by the Lilai Pharmaceutical Factory
他後來被那個理來藥廠挖取
as their research director
當他們的研究室主任
Then he became the first academician of Academia Sinica
然後他變成中研院的第一屆院士
So that's actually another person
所以那其實另外一個人
But after he went to reason
可是他去理來之後
we didn't hear that
我們沒有聽到說
Another big breakthrough, right?
又有一個很大的突破對不對
then why
那為什麼呢
Logically speaking, we imagined
照理講我們想像中
he got to a place
他到了一個地方
Lilai Pharmaceutical Factory fully supports him
理來藥廠全力支持他
Then he became the director for decades
然後當主任他做了幾十年
best environment
最好的環境
Why is there no research result?
為什麼反而研究不出成果呢
So someone would say the other way around
所以有人會反過來說
maybe there's something of value over there
可能那邊有價值的東西
but something of value
但有價值的東西
Maybe not as much as we think
也許沒有我們想的這麼多
I'm sorry everyone today
對不起我今天大家
I have been trying to repeat the positions of both sides in
我一直企圖把兩邊的立場反覆的在
keep him active in our minds over and over again
反覆的在讓他活躍在我們腦裡
because i feel like i said
因為我覺得就像我講的
This period of history is indeed still developing and controversial.
這段歷史的確是還在發展中還有爭議的歷史
Even Du Congming would take a
以至杜聰明會採取一個
The hope that is embraced and the attitude that overcomes the fear
又懷抱的希望又很藉勝恐懼的態度
Then I personally stand in this position
然後我個人也是站在這樣的立場
to write this history
來寫這段歷史
so i feel like saying
所以我會覺得說
I am indeed the same as Du Congming
我的確跟杜聰明一樣
because of hope
因為懷抱的希望
So I will study these seriously
所以我會這麼認真的來研究這些
History of Proven Success
被證明成功的歷史
so that the kind of origin of our story
以至於使得我們故事起源那種
I think it is because based on the development of science now
覺得說因為基於現在科學的發展
The old thing was that we completely broke with him
以前的東西是我們跟他完全斷裂
he must be worthless
他一定沒有價值
There is absolutely no need to give up
拋棄也絕對不用捨不得
I think that position is problematic
那個立場我覺得是有問題的
But does it mean
可是是不是表示說
On the other side there is a very large vault
另外一邊有一個非常大的保庫
or a completely different way of thinking
或一種完全另類的思考方式
That is to say, this is another question
就是說這個又是另外一個問題
then i don't...
那我不...
That's me as a history student
就是我作為一個歷史學姐
I want to be special...
是想特別...
In particular, take a more cautious stance
特別的採取一個比較小心的一個立場
to discover the attitudes of this study
來發掘這個研究的態度
So I deliberately echo everyone's opinions on the one hand.
所以我故意一方面呼應大家的意見
On the other hand, some opposing opinions
另外一方面提出一些反面的意見
Come for your reference
來給大家參考
OK nothing else
OK 還沒什麼其他的
question
問題
yes over there
是 那邊
Let me reply to the paragraph just now
我再回應一下剛剛那一段
That is to say, one of our partners just talked about
就是說其實我們剛剛有一個夥伴有談到
just need some time to use
就是需要有些在用的時候
Other unapproved medicines are effective
其他的沒有核准的藥效出來
Then this part actually you push it back
那這個部分其實你把它反推回去
This is also the biggest advantage in Chinese medicine
這也是漢醫裡面最大的優勢
I just have used it for thousands of years
我就是已經用了幾千年
there are some medicines
那其實有一些藥
It has produced some clinical effects
它是有產生一些臨床的效果
That's confirmed that its possible interactions won't kill
那已經印證到它的可能互作用不會醫死的
So on such a basis
所以在這樣一個基礎之下
If it is developed from its medicinal effect
如果從它的藥效裡面再去發展出來
find out which part of the word it might work
找出它可能有效的部分的話
The so-called reverse research
那它所謂的逆向的這種研究
it becomes ill to soto
它就變成不适向蘇東
How many people do you have to die to find a new drug
你只要一死多少人才能找到一個新藥
this may be one of the
這可能就當中的
I think Han Yi is in the research
我是覺得漢一在研究裡面
He made me a data base
他做我一個data base
a good starting point
一個很好的一個出發點
I suddenly thought of someone I could ask you for advice
我突然想到一個可以跟大家請教
It is an open trial that has been done for thousands of years in the past
就是過去做了幾千年的open trial
open trial is also
open trial也是
And now I think it’s time to do double blind placebo
然後現在覺得說是應該要做double blind placebo
So I did this in Xili
所以是在西裏面也是做過這種
it is open
它是open的
Or open lab use
或者說是open lab use
or it was the beginning
或者本來就是開始的時候
try to see if it works
試試看是不是有用
It was open at that time
那時候是open的
so in fact
所以事實上
I also said that the history above helped to open it
我又說是歷史上面是幫忙做了open的
think it works
覺得有效
Otherwise there is no evidence at all
要不然完全沒有證據
say try it
說本來試試看
not like this
不是這樣子
so i think over here he sees this
所以我想這邊他看到這一點
So in fact there is quite a lot of evidence
所以事實上是有蠻多evidence的
this is very promising
這個很有希望
he wants to push
他想極力推
you'll talk about it later
你待會都講出來了
I just want to learn my experience
我只是想我的心得再學一下
is sorry
是 不好意思
I want to go back to that big brother Bran just now
我想回一下剛剛那個大胞伯蘭
I want to study the law
我想在研究法上面
We cannot fall into this Western medicine
我們不能落入這個西方醫學的
that subject
那個科就
Because of traditional Chinese medicine, make Dazu Bolan
因為中藥的話要做大胞伯蘭
it has an inherent difficulty
它有一個先天的困難
i just wanted to say yes
我剛只是想說是
This is Western medicine with that
這是西醫有那個
Then you have to do Cleaner Trial
然後你這邊要做Cleaner Trial
Cleaner Trial words
Cleaner Trial的話
In fact, the traditional Chinese medicine
事實上是當時對中藥
how to do the best
是要怎麼樣子做最好
i'm not here to discuss
我不是在這邊討論
i just say yes
我只是說是
In fact it is
事實上是
If it was him
如果說是他當初
When people criticize
這邊被人家批評的時候
He said it's actually been done
他講說事實上都已經做過了
It's not like experimenting on humans
並不是說在人體當實驗
Then you are an experiment
那你當實驗就是
He actually doesn't have this at all
他事實上是完全是沒有這個
suddenly remembered
突然想起來
This seems to be useful today
今天這個好像可以有用
no evidence
沒有Evidence
I just talked about Evidence
我剛講說Evidence
Actually maybe not
事實上也許是並沒有
But for thousands of years
但是歷史上面幾千年來
there is
是有
It made him feel confident
是有讓他覺得有信心的
So the point is
所以這一點就是
Maybe I didn't get Appreciation from others at the beginning
應該當初也許沒有得到人家的Appreciation
but maybe this is the reason
但是也許是這個原因
will try to push over there
會極力在往那邊推
What I was going to say just now is the double-blind talk
我剛剛要講的就是那個雙盲的話
In Chinese medicine, because the medicine in Chinese medicine has its own taste
在中醫因為中醫裡面那個藥本身就有味道
So if we use the method of Western medicine to study
所以如果說用西醫的方式研究
Can't use double blind
沒辦法用雙盲
Because the patient knows that the taste is different
因為病人一看就知道那個味道不一樣
But if it is Chinese medicine
那可是如果說是中藥
do you want to ask you
是不是想請教您
That is to say, it is Chinese medicine, right?
就是說是中藥是不是
Or should we go to the scientific side?
還是應該往科學化那邊走啊
If it is extracted
那如果是萃取的話
that's more hopeful
那就比較有希望
If you use scientific Chinese medicine, that step is fine.
科學中藥的話那一步就可以
It should be going that way
應該是往那邊走的話
the shorter the distance
那就距離越短
At present, scientific Chinese medicine has a certain evalence
那目前科學中藥有一定的evalence
over there
在那邊
That is to say, there are some schemes to do it this way.
就是說有一些方計它其實這樣做出來
it does work
它確實是有效的
Okay, so we're running out of time.
好 那我們時間也差不多了
so i think
所以我想
I will first enounce
我先enounce一下
It's the next month next time
就是下一次下個月的這個
just support
就是支持想
The program I want to try is in October
想驗的節目是10月份的
It's our side
是想驗是我們這邊
Cai Dingping of the hard science center of Songyuan Academy
宋院院的硬科中心的蔡定平
Special Review Researcher and Director
特評研究員跟主任
Lecturer on this new era of photonics
主講這個光子新紀元
should be a very good speech
應該是非常精彩的演講
I hope you will sign up
希望各位報名參加
OK then we are very grateful this time
OK 那我們這次非常感謝
Dr. Ray shared with us this
雷博士跟我們分享這位
This is a very wonderful historical story
這個非常精彩的一個歷史的故事
we have a lot to inspire
我們有很多啟發性
There's a lot to think about
跟有很多可以去思考的地方
Is it a round of applause? Thank you.
是不是熱烈掌聲來 謝謝
Thank him
謝謝他